<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Concubinage and poligamy disprov'd, or, The divine institution of marriage betwixt one man, and one woman only, asserted in answer to a book, writ by John Butler, B.D. for which he was presented as follows : We the grand jury, sworn to enquire for the body of the city of London, on Wednesday, the first day of December, 1697, present one John Butler, for writing and publishing a wicked pamphlet : wherein he maintains concubinage to be lawful, and which may prove very destructive to divers families, if not timely suppress'd.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1558</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12409796</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12409796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 662:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Concubinage and poligamy disprov'd, or, The divine institution of marriage betwixt one man, and one woman only, asserted in answer to a book, writ by John Butler, B.D. for which he was presented as follows : We the grand jury, sworn to enquire for the body of the city of London, on Wednesday, the first day of December, 1697, present one John Butler, for writing and publishing a wicked pamphlet : wherein he maintains concubinage to be lawful, and which may prove very destructive to divers families, if not timely suppress'd.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>J. B. --  (John Butler). --  True state of the case.</term>
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61505:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61505:1"/>
            <p>Concubinage <hi>and</hi> Poligamy DISPROV'D: OR, THE Divine Inſtitution of Marriage BETWIXT ONE MAN, AND One Woman only, ASSERTED.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to a Book, writ by <hi>John Butler,</hi> B. D. for which he was preſented as follows:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We the Grand Jury, ſworn to Enquire for the Body of the City of</hi> London, <hi>on</hi> Wedneſday, <hi>the Firſt Day of</hi> December, 1697. <hi>Preſent one</hi> John Butler, <hi>for Writing and Publiſhing a Wicked Pamphlet; wherein he maintains Concubinage to be Lawful, and which may prove very deſtructive to divers Families, if not timely Suppreſs'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Eum qui duas habet <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xores comitatur Infamia,</hi> 
               <bibl>Legi Imperial. Lib. 9. Tit. 9. Leg. 18.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 23. 14.</bibl> 
               <hi>I have ſeen alſo in the Prophets of</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>an horrible thing; they commit Adultery, and walk in Lies; they ſtrengthen alſo the Hands of the Evil Doers, that none doth r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rn from his Wickedneſs.</hi> Ver. 15. <hi>From the Prophets of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>is Prophaneneſs gone forth into all the Land.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> in <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wick-Lane,</hi> 1698. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61505:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61505:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory. TO <hi>John Butler,</hi> B. D. Aſſerter of the Lawfulueſs of Concubinage.</head>
            <p>IT is now become uſual for Authors to ſet off their Performances, by dedicating them to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Patrons; and therefore I hope you will not blame me for Dedicating the following Sheets to your felf. Your Book, for any thing I know, conſidering the Scope of it, and the Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Author, is unpreſidented. You have been at a great deal of Pains, to write an Apology for the Modiſh Practice of keeping a Miſs. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency
<pb facs="tcp:61505:3"/> of the Cuſtom had already abated much of it's Odium; ſo that there wanted nothing but your finiſhing Stroke, to commend it to us from the Pulpit as <hi>Sacred and Holy,</hi> which you have Generouſly done in your 34th Page, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, good Sir, to which of the Saints will you turn, or whom ſhall we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low as a Patron of your <hi>Reform'd Concubinage? Adam</hi> neither had, nor was allowed any Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binc; and the firſt that we find upon Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to have been Guilty of <hi>Poligamy,</hi> was <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech,</hi> one of <hi>Cain</hi>'s Poſterity. I am afraid that the Holineſs of the firſt Practitioner will ſcarcely be able to Hallow the Practice. If we come to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the Faithful, we don't find that he made uſe of any Concubine till his Wife advis'd him to it; and that ſhe did not neither, till ſhe her ſelf was paſt Childbearing, by the Ordinary Courſe of Nature. So that if we muſt be reſiricted to the ſame Conditions, the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants will ſcarcely thank you for your Kindneſs.</p>
            <p>In the next place, you leave us mightily in the Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, not only as to the time when, but likewiſe as to the Number of Concubines we may Lawfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. We don't find that <hi>Abraham</hi> had above one at a time, yet his Grandſon <hi>Jacob</hi> had two or three: Now, pray, Sir, which of the two muſt be our Standard? Or what is to be the Rule of <hi>the Reform'd Concubinage</hi> you propoſe? <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> had the Conſent of their Wives, and the firſt of them ſent away his Miſs, and kept his Wife. But; for you, Sir, if we may believe <hi>Martha Perkins,</hi> you have ſent away your Wife,
<pb facs="tcp:61505:3"/> and kept your <hi>Miſs.</hi> Pardon me, Sir, if I take <hi>Miſs</hi> and <hi>Concubine</hi> to be Synommous Terms; for I am not Maſter of Logick enough to diſtinguiſh betwixt them, according to your Deſcription of the latter.</p>
            <p>But the Liberty of Poligamy, or Concubinage, is not the only thing wherein you have vindicated the Original Right of Mankind; You have put a Greater Obligation upon the Age ſtill, by making every man a Judg in his own Cauſe; nay, and an Executioner too; for you have not only adjudg'd <hi>Martha Perkins</hi> to be an unjuſt Deſertrice, but have diſpos'd of her Property at your own hand, by taking <hi>Mary Tomkins</hi> into her Bed, without Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication either to Church or State, or receiving any Approbation from them. So that it's no Fault of yours, if all Mankind don't, according to your Laudable Example, ſhake off all Subjection to them, and re-aſſume their Primitive Liberty.</p>
            <p>But at the ſame time, Sir, how ſuch Practiſes can agree with the Laws of God, and the Laws of the Land, to which you ought to conform your ſelf as a Chriſtian, and a Subject, you would do well to inform us. You muſt not think to ſatisfie the Curioſity of this Age, by referring us to the diſputed Practiſes of the Patriarchs, which were not found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on any Poſitive Command, nor yet to ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Concubinage found among Chriſtians in <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s time, or before; nor to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Iſſue of Concubines now and then to the Chief Seats of Civil Government; Nay, nor to God's making uſe of the Children of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage
<pb facs="tcp:61505:4"/> ſometimes to be Inſtruments of his Glory. None of theſe are ſufficient to ſatisfie our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and much leſs our Conſcience, which in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this Importance, expects to be aſſur'd by Revelation.</p>
            <p>God allow'd but one Wife to <hi>Adam</hi> when the World was to be Peopled at firſt; nor any more but one Wife a peice to <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons, when it was to be Peopled a ſecond time. And the reaſon of this was as we are inform'd by <hi>Malachi, Becauſe he would have a Holy Seed,</hi> which inſinuates ſtrongly, <hi>That Concubinage is unholy. Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> tho Guiltieſt of all Mankind yet durſt not venture to teach the Lawfulneſs of Concubinage according to your Practice; but tho he had been polluted thereby himſelf, gives precepts full of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to others, adviſing <hi>Them to rejoyce with the Wife of their Youth, and to let her Breaſts ſatisfy them at all times,</hi> Prov. 5. 15. Nor is there throughout the whole Scripture more Emphatical and Paſſionate Exhortations to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Strange Women, and more Lively De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of Whoredom, and the danger of it, then is to be found in the Book of the <hi>Proverbs.</hi> The Pen-man having ſuffered Shipwrack on thoſe Shelves himſelf, was therefore the more fit to paint out the <hi>danger of them</hi> to others, which he has accordingly done; ſo far was he from recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Practice to others, as you do,</p>
            <p>It is alſo certain that our Saviour and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles have commanded, that <hi>every Man ſhould have his own Wife, and every Woman her
<pb facs="tcp:61505:4"/> own Husband.</hi> Nor is there the leaſt Veſtige of <hi>Concubinage</hi> to be found allowed in <hi>the New Teſtament.</hi> So that it is exceeding ſtrange that you ſhould ſtretch your Commiſſion, and wreſt Texts to teach us <hi>Concubinage,</hi> eſpecially when the Age has more need of a <hi>Curb</hi> than a <hi>Spur</hi> as to that matter.</p>
            <p>But above all things in your Book, thoſe Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Reflections upon the Conception and Birth of our bleſſed Saviour choak me moſt. Had you no other way to defend your own practice but by ſuch profane Alluſions? Don't the Scriptures teach you, <hi>That there is no ſuch thing as Marrying and giving in Marriage in the Kingdom of Heaven?</hi> Can there be any A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogy betwixt the bleſſed Virgins Immaculate and Wonderful Coneeption, and the Pregnancy of others before Marriage? Is there any ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude betwixt that which is done by the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence of God, without any poſſible Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of humane Corruption, and the practice of <hi>Concubinage?</hi> Really, Sir, this Notion appears to me ſo very foul and horrid, that I think there can be no better Advice given to you than that which the Apoſtle gave to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Acts 8. 22. <hi>Repent therefore of this thy Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thy Heart may be forgiven thee.</hi> Had you taken heed unto your ſelf, and to your Doctrine, according to the Apoſtle's Advice to <hi>Timothy,</hi> you would never have been guilty of ſuch a Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, nor have advanced any ſuch Principles.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61505:5"/>
            <p>In the next place, Sir, let me ask you, <hi>What was it you ſaw in Concubinage, or what migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Profit have you reap'd thereby your ſelf, that you do with ſo much Zeal recommend it to others?</hi> Had you but look't into Hiſtory, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sacred or Profane, you would have found that the Natural Effects of it were, the breach of the Peace of Families, Quarrels, Murders, and all manner of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs. It had its riſe from <hi>Cains</hi> Family, and you know that he was of <hi>that wicked one;</hi> Murder and Whoredom had both of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em their Original from the ſame vile Parent, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs and Hatred of true Religion, have always ſince gone hand in hand, as you may ſee abundantly proved in the Book call'd, <hi>Gods Judgment againſt Whoring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to your own Family, You own that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of your firſt Marriage are Rebellious and Diſobedient, that they have offered Violence to your own Perſon, and continue to oppreſs and ſlander you, that your firſt Wife hath deſerted you, <hi>[as you ſay]</hi> becauſe you diſinherited her Eldeſt Son a Papiſt, and <hi>[as ſhe ſays]</hi> becauſe you had got your Maid with child before-hand, and you add that ſhe and her Sons have unjuſtly poſſeſs'd themſelves of your Inheritance. Theſe, and ſuch as theſe, are the Bleſſed effects of your own Concubinage, and yet you are ſo good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd as to recommend it to others. Let's ſuppoſe now your children by <hi>Mary Tomkins,</hi> come alſo to years of Maturity, will not they have the ſame Rancour againſt <hi>Martha Perkins</hi> and her
<pb facs="tcp:61505:5"/> Children, as ſhe and hers have againſt them? Will not both Broods be enrag'd to find their reſpective Mothers treated as an Harlot, and is not this the Natural Reſult of your Concubinage.</p>
            <p>Then as to the Opinion that the World enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of you, It cannot be ſuppos'd to be very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable. The worſt of Men, abominate a Leud Clergy-man, and you own your ſelf that you are Accounted ſuch an one, and let me tell you that your Defence will be far from healing your Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, there's no way left you for that, but to confeſs and forſake. You will not find that Men of Senſe and Probity will take your Arguments as unanſwerable; and tho ſome of your Brethren you ſay, have giv'n no reply to what you return'd as an Anſwer to their Reproof, all others will not therefore think themſelves obliged to keep ſilent. The Cauſe concerns the welfare of our Souls and Bodys, Poſterities and Families too much, to let you paſs without a Publick Anſwer, tho hitherto you have eſcap'd any Publick Cenſure more than the Preſentment of the Grand Jury; The Author of this Reply, has no Perſonal Acquaintance with you, nor pick againſt you, and if in ſome Places, you find that he hath treated you ſharply, it's no more than what he thought the Cauſe requir'd. It ſeem'd indeed a ſort of a Paradox to him, that a Man ſhould pretend to ſo much Conſcience of keeping an Oath to a Temporal Prince, from which his Abdication and the Cauſes of it, abſolv'd him in the Opinion both of Church and State, and yet make no ſcruple of breaking his Marriage Vow to
<pb facs="tcp:61505:6"/> God and his Wife, by taking another into he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bed before his Cauſe was heard and much leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd. That he himſelf ſhould take upon him to be Judge in his own Cauſe, and yet not allow the <hi>Supreme Power</hi> of the Nation to be Judge in theirs againſt a Prince, whom he owns to <hi>have Acted Tyrannically, by erecting an High Commiſſion Court to ſuperſede the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of all others, and to Act in favour of Perſons Popiſhly Inclin'd.</hi> That Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> ſhould allow Deſertion in his own Wife, to be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cauſe of Divorce, and of Marrying another, and yet ſcruple to own that Tyranny and Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are not ſufficient to diſſolve the Contract betwixt King and People, and to juſtify their ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another upon the Throne; Says, that he is a very partial Caſuiſt, and gives the Reader very much cauſe to ſuſpect his ſincerity.</p>
            <p>In the next place let me ask you, what mighty bleſſings they are which the <hi>Turks</hi> reap from their Poligamy? You cannot pretend that it hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their Off-ſpring, and made them Populous. For daily experience teaches us, that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are now very much exhauſted; which is the Natural conſequence of Poligamy at laſt, tho it may prove otherwiſe for an Age or two at firſt. The reaſons of this are obvious. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Too much Venery conſumes a Mans Bones and Fleſh, and the Iſſue of ſuch Conſumptive and Incontinent Parents, will in time enfeeble the whole Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:61505:6"/>2. A Mans making uſe of more Wives than one at a time, occaſions the Women to think that they ought to have the ſame Liberty; How many unhappy Inſtances does our own Nation afford of this, that the Mans going aſtray, hath made the Woman take that ſame Courſe, which all Men own to be deſtructive to Propagation, and muſt in time diminiſh the Number of People?</p>
            <p n="3">3. When a Man hath ſuch a Numerous Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he cannot ſufficiently provide for; then all of them come to be neglected, and to want the neceſſary conveniencies of Life, which ſhortens their Days, and Breeds Naſty and Contagious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers amongſt them, as is evident from the frequent Plagues amongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> whereof this is aſſign'd as one Principal Cauſe, and its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent enough amongſt the children of common Beggars, and the Pooreſt Sort, many of whom Periſh by Naſty Diſeaſes, which renders them Loathſome to the Eyes and Noſes of thoſe that walk the Streets.</p>
            <p>And if <hi>Poligamy</hi> were allow'd in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to your Propoſal, we ſhould quickly find that our greateſt Eſtates would be much too ſmall to maintain the numerous Offſpring of Perſons of Quality, according to their Birth; ſo that they muſt quickly be reduced to Miſery, and the Original Families ſuddenly periſh. For the Children of one Wife would think they had as good right to be provided for out of their Father's Eſtates, as thoſe of another; Which if they were, it would ſpeedily diſmember the largeſt
<pb facs="tcp:61505:7"/> Patrimonies that any of our Nobility enjoy and if they were not, it would occaſion endleſs Quarrels and Murders betwixt Brethren and Siſters. If you had but looked into our antient Hiſtory, and conſider'd what a Miſerable, Bruitiſh, and Defenceleſs People our Anceſtors were, at the time of the <hi>Roman</hi> Invaſion, when <hi>Poligamy</hi> was allowed amongſt them, you would quickly find what I ſay to be true.</p>
            <p>You muſt alſo know, that the Imperial Laws condemn <hi>Poligamy,</hi> Lib. 9. Tit. 9. Leg. 18. <hi>Eum qui habet duas Uxores comitatur Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, i. e.</hi> He is counted infamous that hath two Wives. <hi>Diocleſian</hi> made a Law likewiſe againſt having of two Wives: <hi>Cod. Lib. 5. Tit. 5. Leg. 2</hi> And the Chriſtian Emperors, <hi>Theodoſius, Arcadius,</hi> and <hi>Honorius,</hi> would not ſuffer the <hi>Jews</hi> that lived in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, to have many Wives, as may be ſeen by their Laws, <hi>Cod. de judaei. Leg.</hi> So un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly have you appealed to the Practice of the Antient Chriſtians, either Magiſtrates or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as Patrons of <hi>Concubinage.</hi> You know likewiſe that St. <hi>Hierome</hi> condemns <hi>Lamech</hi> as the firſt, <hi>Qui unam coſtam diſtraxit in duas,</hi> who made two Ribs of one.</p>
            <p>Nor can it be unknown to you, that Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men committing Adultery, were for ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from their Miniſtery, Diſtinct. <hi>81. C. 11, 12.</hi> That the <hi>Ancyran Synod</hi> impoſed Seven Years Pennance upon the Adulterer; and that the Council of <hi>Neocaeſarea</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed,
<pb facs="tcp:61505:7"/> that if a Miniſter's Wife fell into Adultery, he ſhould diſmiſs her, or elſe leave his Miniſtry, and by the <hi>Eliberine</hi> Council he was denied for ever the Communion of the Church, if he did not diſmiſs her, and that it was likewiſe Decreed, that the Adulterer ſhould not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to Marry with the Adultreſs; yet you own that you had juſt Cauſe to ſuſpect your Wife, and can prove ſeveral ſuſpicious Tokens of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs, <hi>p. 18.</hi> and yet never offer'd to put her away: And ſhe accuſes you of committing Adultery with her Maid before ſhe left you, and yet you took your Maid into her Bed, without any Application either to Church or State, notwithſtanding the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Controverſies betwixt you and your Wife. Theſe are ſuſpicious Tokens of an Inordinate Love; for which, had you but made uſe of the firſt and ſecond Remedies preſcribed by the Heathens, <hi>viz. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Abſtinence and Time, you had been in no danger of the third Remedy <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an Halter, though it had been better you ſhould have had a Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone hang'd about your Neck, and been thrown into the middle of the Sea, than to have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuch Offence as you have done to the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Nor can you be ignorant neither, that many ſatisfying Anſwers have been given to your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, from the Polygamy of the Patriarchs and Jews: As 1. That if there had been any Relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Law of <hi>Monogamy,</hi> inſtituted by
<pb facs="tcp:61505:8"/> God in Paradice, it would have been by a written Law and Expreſs Scripture. 2. That if this had been allowed for Procreation, it had been moſt Neceſſary to be granted unto <hi>Adam</hi> in the beginning of the World, and to <hi>Noah</hi> in revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and re-peopling the World. And 3. That Polygamy, or marrying of many Wives, render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Solomon</hi> unfit for Procreation, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by his ſmall Poſterity. And, 4. That the Law of <hi>Monogamy</hi> being revived by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and brought back to the firſt Inſtitution, was to take place, not for the Time paſt, but for the Time to come, as all other poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Laws of Natione do: So that though Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamy might be then tolerated as an Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for a time, in thoſe which were newly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted; yet it cannot be ſo now.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add that if the firſt inſtitution of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, between one Man an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one Woman at a time be once broken, there's no other Limitation to be found in the Scriptures; whence it follows, that if more be allowed then one, a Man may have as many as he pleaſes, So that it will be hard to bring it to a Medium. Some perhaps will plead for King <hi>Charles II's.</hi> Number as a Standard, and others it may be, will be ſatisfied with no fewer than <hi>Solomon,</hi> and ſo our Nobility and Gentry (if your Project take place) ſhould have Kennels of Concubines, as now they have of Hounds. And what Inconveniences this might occaſion, you may know by your own Incontinence, thoſe Poor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men muſt looſe their Youth, and Teeming time,
<pb facs="tcp:61505:8"/> without any hopes of having Nature ſatisfied; For being another Mans Property, no body elſe muſt meddle with them, and ſo they muſt either burn and languiſh, or commit Whoredom, nay, perhaps beſtiality. Their own Stallion (for Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band he is not) muſt ſpeedily be either enfeebled, or neglect ſome or all of them, as we find in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſuerus,</hi> who did not call for his Beautiful and Beloved <hi>Eſther</hi> in Thirty Days together. And the reſt of his Concubines were never brought to him except he delighted in any of them, and call'd her by Name, yet they were ſhut up and kept cloſe by the Keeper of the Women. So that here was a Great Number of Females rendred uſeleſs for Propagation, beſides the Tentations they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to, of being baſe with <hi>Eunuchs</hi> and their own neareſt Relations.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, pray conſider whether theſe and the other Reaſons that you will meet with in this Book, be not much more ſolid againſt <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage,</hi> than any that you have advanc'd for it. And if your Conſcience be convinced, be not aſhamed to Retract what you have ſo unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly writ upon this Head. St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who was much a Learneder Divine, and better Man than you can pretend to be, did not think it unbecoming him to Recant his Errors, and to take ſhame to himſelf for his Youthful Luſts; but Yours can ſcarcely paſs under that denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who went into your Maids Bed, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Lived Forty Years with a <hi>Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61505:9"/>
            <p>Your Looſe Book hath done a World of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief in the Nation; and therefore it concerns you, as you would have the pardon of God, and his Church for the ſame, to make your Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Recantation as publick as your <hi>Crime;</hi> Which that you may do, is the worſt that the Author of this Book wiſhes you.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61505:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Concubinage</hi> Diſproved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAD a Pamphlet of this Nature been writ by an avowed Debauchee, or a Play-houſe Beau, it had been no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Surprize: But to have any thing Printed in Defence of <hi>Concubinage</hi> by a Batchelor of Divinity, and a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may Juſtly aſtoniſh us. Such a thing might be accounted Natural, in a Prieſt of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Mother of Harlots, and of the Abominations of the Earth; but for a Miniſter of the Reformed Church to do ſo groſs a thing, is altogether unſufferable.</p>
            <p>Time was when the Reverend Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> was degraded by thoſe that called themſelves the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe he maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Doctrine of Self-defence againſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, or others; which is the Inſtinct of pure Nature: There's much more reaſon for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61505:10"/> the Governours of the Church to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as zealous now in cenſuring Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> for writing in defence of <hi>Concubinage;</hi> which is one of the Effects of depraved Nature: And this I think they are the more concern'd to do, becauſe in his Title-Page he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make way for his Doctrine by the Authority of his Character.</p>
            <p>It is certain this Author can find nothing either in the Articles, Homilies, or Canons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to defend his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples or Practice; So that he cannot plead any Authority from her, whatever he may do from his being in Orders. Nor is that Venerable Society any thing oblig'd to him for the Character which he aſſumes to himſelf of being a Miniſter of the <hi>True Church of England;</hi> The Natural Conſequence of which Expreſſion is, That ſomewhere or other there is a Falſe one. By ſome Hints in his Pamphlet, as, <hi>That he has been accuſed of being an Enemy to the Government;</hi> and <hi>that he is ſuch an one as hath kept his Oaths to his hurt,</hi> &amp;c. I preſume he may be a <hi>Non-Juror;</hi> and if that be the Caſe, we know what he means by his True Church; and to ſay the Truth of them, <hi>ſuch Parſon, ſuch People,</hi> was never more fitly applied. It has been obſerved all along ſince the Revolution, that moſt of the Whores are in King <hi>James</hi>'s Intereſt, nor will it be any great Loſs to King <hi>William,</hi> if this <hi>Advocate of Whoring</hi> be thrown into the Scale.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61505:10"/>
            <p>It's none of my buſineſs to enter upon the Merits of the Cauſe betwixt him and his <hi>Quondam</hi> Wife. It's probable enough, nay, certainly true, if we may believe his own word, that he and ſhe both are guilty of ſuch Iniquity as ought to be puniſh'd by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; and in recommending his Book to the Care and Enquiry of the Bench, I Joyn cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially with <hi>the Grand Jury of London,</hi> who in this, and other Preſentments, have behaved themſelves as became good Men and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <p>Before I come to touch upon his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>in Defence of Concubinage,</hi> I find it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make ſome previous Remarks.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, That our Author is not to be taken as an Indifferent Perſon or Judge in this Caſe, becauſe it is his own Practice he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends; and the Depravation of Mankind is now ſo very great, that we ſhall have the moſt horrid Crimes, as Murder, Aſſaſſinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and what not, defended by the Criminals who commit them.</p>
            <p>The next is, That our Author, according to what is ſaid of other Evil Men and Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, waxes worſe and worſe; for in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his Book he ſeems only to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate his own particular Caſe, as having a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting Wife, and being under an Impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of having Juſtice done him; and therefore he thought it lawful for him <hi>to go in to his Maid;</hi> But in the latter end of his Pamphlet he ſets up for a General Concubinage, ev'n
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61505:11"/> 
               <hi>during the Life and Co-habitation of Lawful Wives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things being laid down as neceſſary to give the Reader a precaution as to what ſort of an Author we have to deal with, I come now to conſider his Arguments.</p>
            <p>The Firſt he offers is page 9. Viz. <hi>That he was guilty of no other, nor greater Fornication with his Maid, than</hi> Abraham, <hi>the Father of the Faithful, was guilty of, when purely for Iſſues ſake, and not of any Luſtful Concupiſcence, he went in to</hi> Hagar, <hi>his Wifes Maid, or in to</hi> Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turah, <hi>his Concubine, in the Life-time of</hi> Sarah, <hi>his Wife. Now</hi> Abraham <hi>was not charged with any thing of Fornication in that Caſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was acquitted by God Almighty, as purely and truly Innocent; but the Caſe of this Reſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent is much eaſier than that of</hi> Abraham; <hi>foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as at the time aforeſaid</hi> Abraham <hi>had a Wife then in his Bed with him, but this Reſpondent had no Wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANSWER.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our Author owns that <hi>Abraham</hi> did not go in to <hi>Hagar</hi> out of any Luſtful Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, but purely for Iſſues ſake; but page 9. he ſays of himſelf, <hi>That he is one of thoſe of whom our Saviour hath declared,</hi> All men cannot receive this ſaying, <hi>Matth. 19. 10. and of whom St.</hi> Paul <hi>hath deelared,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 9. It is better to marry than to burn; <hi>and that he was not Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61505:11"/> endowed with the Gift of Continency from Heaven.</hi> Whence it follows, That our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor by his own confeſſion, went in to his Maid out of a Principle of Incontinence, and burning Luſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This appears yet more plain: Whereas he owns, <hi>that</hi> Abraham <hi>went in to</hi> Hagar <hi>purely for Iſſues ſake,</hi> he having none at that time; which was not our Author's Caſe; for he confeſſes, page 4. that he had Lawful Iſſue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by his Wife; which demonſtrates, Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> himſelf being Judge, that his Caſe and <hi>Abraham</hi>'s were not the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Abraham</hi> took <hi>Hagar</hi> to Wife by <hi>Sarah</hi>'s Conſent; and tho not with the uſual Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Marriage, yet 'twas undoubtedly in a Publick manner; but Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> owns, page 18. that his Wife was ſo far from conſenting to his taking of his Maid <hi>Mary Tomkins,</hi> that ſhe gives it out as one cauſe of her deſerting him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It does not appear by any thing our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſays, that his Marriage with <hi>Mary Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> was any other than <hi>Congreſſus Furtivus,</hi> a <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Wedding: or <hi>Nuptiae Caninae,</hi> as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> calls it ſomewhere.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Inſtance of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s going in to <hi>Keturah,</hi> during <hi>Sarahs</hi> Life, is falſe; for it appears that <hi>Sarah</hi> was then dead, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. 1. and <hi>Hagar</hi> and her Son <hi>Iſhmael</hi> were ſent away before that by God's own appointment, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. So that this Inſtance makes nothing at all for his purpoſe. But it looks very ill in a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61505:12"/> as Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> pretends to be, thus to miſ-quote Scripture: It argues that he is glad of any covering, tho it were but of Fig-leaves to cover his Nakedneſs.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> cannot but know that <hi>P.</hi> Martyr, and other Commentators upon the Place, are of Opinion, that the Occaſion of <hi>Sarah</hi>'s giving this Advice, and of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s accepting of it, was her own Barrenneſs, the advanced Age of 'em both, and fear that they ſhould no otherwiſe have the Promiſed Seed, to which I hope our Author will not pretend there is any thing parallel in his Caſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whereas he ſays <hi>that Abraham was not charged with any thing of Fornication in that Caſe, but rather was acquitted by God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty as truely and purely Innocent.</hi> It were to be wiſh'd he would produce ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for his Aſſertion; In my Opinion the Diſpleaſure of God againſt this Practice of the <hi>Patriarch</hi> appears very plain, as has been obſerv'd by the Author of that uſeful Book, newly publiſhed, entituled, <hi>God's Judgments againſt Whoring; being an Eſſay towards a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Hiſtory of it for above Five Thouſand Years,</hi> Viz. <hi>That the Peace of</hi> Abraham'<hi>s Family was immediately broke, by</hi> Hagar'<hi>s deſpiſing her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, as ſoon as ſhe found her ſelf pregnant with the Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſed Seed, as ſhe vainly believ'd. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which</hi> Sarah <hi>upbraids</hi> Abraham, <hi>with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er ſelf was the occaſion; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> alſo puniſhed for her unlawful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61505:12"/> firſt, by being ſeverely dealt with by</hi> Sarah, <hi>and then by being thruſt out of the Family, and expos'd to the World, and the cruel Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſeeing her Son die of Thirſt as ſhe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; and inſtead of his being the Promiſed Seed, ſhe and he were both Ignominouſly thruſt out from being Partakers of the Inheritance with</hi> Iſaac.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Polygamy</hi> was at that time common in the World, ſo that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Practice ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred no occaſion of Scandal, whereas our Author well knew that his <hi>Concubinage</hi> with <hi>Mary Tomkins</hi> would unavoidably give Offence, upon which Conſideration alone, he ought to have forborn it, if he had deſign'd to walk according to the Apoſtolical Rule, who had rather never eat Fleſh while he liv'd, tho a thing lawful in it ſelf, than of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend a weak Brother.</p>
            <p n="9">9. His Argument to prove the Lawfulneſs of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Practice, becauſe God did not charge him with any thing of Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is altogether inconcludent; for in the firſt place it is not a ſufficient Ground for us poſitively to ſay that God did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove him for it, becauſe there's nothing of any ſuch Reproof mentioned in the Scripture. <hi>Moſes,</hi> the inſpired Penman, is here giving us an Hiſtorical Account of Matter of Fact, and does not enter upon the Debate of the Lawfulneſs or Unlawfulneſs of the thing. In the next place Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> may as well argue from the Practice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> which we find
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61505:13"/> no where reproved by God that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for a Man to marry two Siſters at one time, whereas all Divines allow, that this is forbidden, both by the Light of Nature and Revelation.</p>
            <p n="10">10. To anſwer once for all, Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Arguments from the <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> for <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligamy</hi> or <hi>Concubinage.</hi> He cannot but know,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Marriage was inſtituted at firſt by God, betwixt one Man and one Woman; ſo that to plead for a Neceſſity of more Husbands or Wives than one at a time, is in effect to arraign the Wiſdom of the firſt Inſtitutor, the All-wiſe God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That when the old World was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and chiefly for Uncleanneſs amongſt other Sins as appears by <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 2. God appointed <hi>Noah</hi> and his three Sons, to take only one Wife each into the Ark with them, ſo that here God commanded the peopling of the World a ſecond time by Marriage betwixt one Man and one Woman, without allowing <hi>Polygamy</hi> or <hi>Concubinage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Text, <hi>Leviticus 18. 18. Neither ſhalt thou take a Wife to her Siſter to vex her, to uncover her Nakedneſs, beſides the other in her Life time.</hi> The beſt Divines do generally underſtand it to be meant of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving two Wives together, firſt, becauſe the Phraſe is ſo uſed elſewhere, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1. 9. the Wings of the Beaſts are ſaid to touch a Woman to her Siſter that is meet together, or touch one another; and ſo <hi>Exod.</hi> 26. 3.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61505:13"/> 
               <hi>the five Curtains ſhall be coupled, the Woman to her Siſter,</hi> that is, together. In the next place, becauſe the Marriage of the Siſter is by Analogy forbidden before <hi>v. 16. Thou ſhalt not uncover the Nakedneſs of thy Brothers Wife, it is thy Brothers Nakedneſs.</hi> Whence by Parity of Reaſon it was equally unlawful to uncover the Siſters Nakedneſs; ſo that this being provided for before, there was no need of repeating it here; thirdly, the Reaſon ſubjoyn'd, <hi>viz.</hi> to vex her, maketh againſt the Joint Marriage of any other, as well as of the Siſter; for the common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of all Ages teaches, that there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Jealouſie and Contention betwixt <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives,</hi> as in the Inſtance of <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Hagar,</hi> juſt now mentioned; and <hi>Annah</hi> and <hi>Penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> the Wives of <hi>Elkanah, 1 Sam.</hi> 1. tho they were not Siſters: And Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> can prove it from his own Experience, that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha Perkins</hi> and <hi>Mary Tomkins,</hi> his two Wives, do vex one another, tho they be not Siſters.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to his Inſtances of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and other Kings, who abounded in Wives and Concubines, they acted therein expreſly contrary to the Law in that caſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 16. where it is ſaid of the King, <hi>Neither ſhall he multiply Wives to himſelf.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt foreſeeing that they who abound in Riches and Power, and eſpecially Princes are more apt to exceed that way than others.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:61505:14"/>5. Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> has no doubt read, that <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus</hi> and others are of Opinion, That the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamy</hi> of the Fathers was diſpens'd with <hi>per inſpirationem internam</hi> by a ſecret Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which cannot, if it were true, juſtifie <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage</hi> under the <hi>New-Teſtament,</hi> from which nothing can be pleaded by any ſuch Diſpenſation.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He muſt needs alſo know that it is the common Opinion of Proteſtant Divines, that it was not probable that God would diſpenſe with a Publick Law by a Private Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore, tho he wink'd at thoſe times of Ignorance, he gave no Allowance to any ſuch Practice, as is plain from <hi>Malachi</hi> 2. 14. 15, 16. Where the Prophet tells the Children of <hi>Iſrael, That the Lord regarded not their Offering, becauſe he had been Witneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thee and the Wife of thy youth, againſt whom thou haſt dealt treacherouſly, yet is ſhe thy Companion, and the Wife of thy Covenant:</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 15. he expoſtulates with them from the firſt Inſtitution of Marriage thus: <hi>And did he make one? yet had he the reſidue of the Spirit, and wherefore one? becauſe he ſought a Godly Seed; therefore take heed to your Spirit, and let none deal treacherouſly againſt the Wife of his Youth;</hi>—and verſe 16. he adds, <hi>For the Lord God of Iſrael ſaith that he hateth putting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> This Prophet liv'd as ſome think in the time of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> or <hi>Darius Longimanus;</hi> but however that is, this is plain, that as in the beginning of the Old-Teſtament, we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61505:14"/> have an Account that God at firſt inſtituted Marriage betwixt one Man and one Woman; ſo by this Prophet, who ſhuts up the Canon of the Old Teſtament, he expoſtulates with his People, for receding from the Primary Inſtitution, which enervates all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> hath brought from thence, in Defence of <hi>Concubinage:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is not the only Caſe, wherein our Author ſhews himſelf to be a <hi>looſe Caſuiſt;</hi> for Page 9. he tells us, <hi>That Incontinency in it ſelf is no Sin, unleſs it be expreſs'd in unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful uſes;</hi> whereas the Apoſtie, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 3. reckons <hi>Incontinent</hi> Men amongſt Truce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakers, Falſe Accuſers, Deſpiſers of thoſe that are Good, and ſuch others as contribute to make up the Perillous Times, that are to come in the laſt days. Mr. <hi>Pool,</hi> in his Criticks on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 5. quotes <hi>Tremellius, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcator, Hammond,</hi> and <hi>Zegerus,</hi> as tranſlating the word, rendred Incontinence (by our Tranſlators) <hi>Concupiſcence of the Fleſh,</hi> and others of 'em render it <hi>Intemperance,</hi> which laſt Word is never taken but in an ill Senſe. <hi>Tremellius</hi> from the <hi>Syriak</hi> tranſlates it <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia,</hi> which ſignifies an unruly raging Luſt which is certainly ſinful; and ſuch Mr. <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi>'s Incontinence appears to have been, when he could not be without a Woman above a Year; one would have thought that a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, who enjoyns Faſting and Prayer to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhou'd rather have tried that Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon himſelf, than have run the hazard
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61505:15"/> of ſuch Inconveniences, as the Titillation of the Fleſh, has already brought upon him. The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>They that are Chriſt's, crucifie the Fleſh with its Luſts and Affections, Gal.</hi> 5. 24. and in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 17. that he <hi>kept his Body under, and brought it into Subjection, leſt when he preach'd to others, he himſelf ſhould be a Caſt-away;</hi> but it ſeems Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> choſe rather to <hi>make proviſion for the Fleſh to fullſil the Luſts thereof.</hi> If he could not have his Wife he would have his Maid; and is not ſatisfied <hi>to break the Commandments himſelf, but teaches o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo to do ſo;</hi> and therefore deſerves <hi>to be called the Leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Saviour's threatning, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 19. and I doubt not but he knows what is meant thereby; <hi>viz.</hi> That he ſhall be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unworthy to be reckoned among the Saints here or hereafter, if he don't break off from his ſins by Repentance. Our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 28. tells us, That they who <hi>Look on a Woman ſo as to Luſt after her, are guilty of Adultery.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells us of thoſe that <hi>have Eyes full of Adultery,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 14. Which demonſtrate clearly enough, that Incontinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the Fountain whence Luſtful Looks pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, is ſinful in it ſelf. Indeed the Natural Appetite of Generation, and multiplying our Species according to the Command of God, is not ſinful in it ſelf, ſo long as it is contain'd within due bounds; but when once it breaks over that, then it becomes Incontinence, and by conſequence ſinful. The Original Word,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61505:15"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, tranſlated <hi>Incontinent,</hi> denotes ſuch, <hi>qui nec in bono nec in malo ſibi conſtant,</hi> they can keep no bounds, but will either be over-much Righteous or over-much Wicked: So that it's plain, Incontinence, which Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> will have to be no ſin, implies the Height of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems he thought himſelf concern'd, in point of Reputation, to maintain, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continence was no ſin, becauſe he owns himſelf to be guilty of it, page 9. Yet if he had but adverted to the ſaying of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 9. which he quotes in the ſame place, <hi>viz, They who cannot contain, let them marry; for it is better to marry than to burn;</hi> he might eaſily have perceiv'd that <hi>Incontinence</hi> and <hi>burning</hi> are Synonymous Terms; for there <hi>burning</hi> is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to <hi>Continency;</hi> the Holy Ghoſt telling us plainly, that they who cannot contain muſt burn, if they do not marry, and therefore provides Marriage as a proper Remedy againſt Incontinency; which if it were not a Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, why ſhould there be any Remedy provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt it.</p>
            <p>Here alſo I think fit to take notice of our Author's diſtorted Notion of Fornication, whereof he ſays, page 8. <hi>A man may be guilty by Exceſs of Carnal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage with his own Wife.</hi> That this Notion of Fornication is very groſs and abſurd, will appear from this one thing, that if a Man may be guilty of Fornication with his own Wife. then he may divorce her when he pleaſes for his own Crime; for our Saviour
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61505:16"/> allows a man to put away his Wife in caſe of Fornication, without any Exception, whether it be with her Husband, or any other man, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 32. So that inſtead of a man's being guilty of Fornication with his own Wife, our Author ſhould have ſaid, of Exceſs in the uſe of the Marriage-bed; for tho Fornication is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times us'd in Scripture to denote Uncleanneſs in general: yet according to the common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of the word, it denotes Uncleanneſs betwixt perſons, that are not married to one another, as was uſually practiſed in thoſe <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nices,</hi> or Vaults under ground, at <hi>Rome</hi> and elſe where; whence the word <hi>Fornication</hi> was deriv'd. Of thoſe Vaults <hi>Socrates, Lib. 5. cap.</hi> 18. gives us a particular account; <hi>viz.</hi> That they were Victualling-houſes under ground, wherein the <hi>Romans</hi> proſtituted Whores, until the Emperor <hi>Theodoſius</hi> order'd them to be pulled down.</p>
            <p>I come next to Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Caſe, as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by himſelf, page 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Viz. <hi>That his Wife denied him the uſe of her Marriage bed ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately (tho ſhe was often intreated to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) for above a Twelvemonth; and therefore he went in to his Maid.</hi> The Neceſſity he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends he lay under was this, <hi>In the firſt place, he had not the Gift of Continency; then it was not convenient for him to marry another without a Lawful Licenſe from a Lawful Authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of a Statute-Law in force: That in the time of this deſertion, Popery had the Supream</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:61505:16"/> 
               <hi>Seat: That there were high Commiſſioners ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding all other Courts in Power, and Acting in favour of Perſons Popiſhly inclin'd, and that his Wife having deſerted him, becauſe of his diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriting his Eldeſt Son for turning Papiſt; No ſentence could be expected from them, according to the Juſtice of Holy writ, becauſe Papiſts hold Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage indiſſolvable, as being one of their ſeven Sacraments without a diſpenſation from the Pope.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> States his own Caſe.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I ſhall give you hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wifes State of the Caſe, as repreſented in her Libel before the Honourable Court of Arches, and quoted by himſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 6. Viz. <hi>That about Ten Years ſince,</hi> John Butler <hi>being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful of his Conjugal Vow committed, the foul Crime of Adultery, with his Servant Maid</hi> Mary Tomkins; <hi>and it being taken Notice of, that ſhe was with Child by him, he and ſhe went into</hi> Holland, <hi>where they liv'd Incontinently for about two Years, and there ſhe brought forth a Baſtard call'd</hi> Mary <hi>to the ſaid</hi> John Butler, <hi>and</hi> p. 35. <hi>That they return'd to</hi> England, <hi>and Live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in an Incontinent manner at</hi> Hammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, <hi>and the ſaid</hi> Mary <hi>hath had four other baſe born Children, begotten by the ſaid</hi> John But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>who hath Lately turn'd his Wife</hi> Mary But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler <hi>out of Doors, and left her deſtitute of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now any Man may ſee that there is a vaſt difference in the Caſes, as they are Stated by Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> and his Wife.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:61505:17"/>
            <p>It is alſo proper to obſerve here, that his Incontinence with <hi>Mary Tomkins</hi> is not the only Uncleanneſs which our Author ſtands charg'd with; for page 8. he owns, <hi>That his ſaid Wife, and his two ungracious Sons, have fill'd the Countrey with many ſlanders and ſuſpicious Reports, of matters ſaid or done by him, above Twenty or Thirty Years ſince; and</hi> Anſwers thus, <hi>Concerning what kindneſſes this Reſpondent might have ſhewed to particular Perſons more then Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, he doth ſolemnly proteſt, that he never had Carnal Knowledge of any ſuch Woman, for whoſe ſake he was aſpers'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus laid down their mutual Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations againſt one another, I ſhall firſt make ſome Remarks upon 'em, and then proceed to conſider Mr. <hi>Butlers</hi> defence.</p>
            <p>It's plain, that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> owns himſelf to be Incontinent, and I think it will appear that he was ſo, to a ſcandalous exceſs from the Matter of Fact, as laid down by himſelf. For 1. He ſays, that he was deſerted by a Wife, whom <hi>p.</hi> 3. he owns, <hi>That he did hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily Love,</hi> which one would think ſhould have been ſufficient of it ſelf, to have reſtrain'd his Concupiſcence for above one year at leaſt, ſeeing moſt modeſt Men do in ordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, think themſelves obliged in Decency to ſtay ſo long unmarried after the Death of a Wife whom they Loved. Much more ſhould an honeſt Man abſtain for the ſake of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Wife ſtill alive.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61505:17"/>2. He owns that he had two ungracious Sons, the Eldeſt of whom he diſinherited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his turning Papiſt; this methinks to a Miniſter of the Goſpel, ſhould have been a Cauſe of Faſting and Prayer, and Mortifying of the Fleſh. To be abandoned by a Loving Wife, afflicted by two ungracious Sons at the ſame time, and one of them turn'd Idolater, and running headlong to Damnation too: Any thing of a Chriſtian would have ſeen the Hand of God, in all this, humbled themſelves before him, afflicted their Souls by ſecret Faſting and Prayer, and have deſir'd the Prayers of the Church, and their particular Chriſtian Friends, in ſuch a pungent Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>If in ſuch a Caſe the Devil had begun to tempt Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> for his Incontinency, Why did he not bring his Body under Subjection by Faſting, Watching and Prayer, according to the Practice of the Apoſtle; who thereby got rid of that Thorn in the Fleſh mentioned, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 7. Which Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> knows many Commentators, and thoſe, none of the leaſt, Note, underſtand to have been <hi>Pruritus Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> the Tickling of the Fleſh, as <hi>Tremellius</hi> renders it from the <hi>Syriack.</hi> But it ſeems, our Author was in this Reſpect like the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees of Old, who would bind heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens upon other Mens backs but would not touch them themſelves with one of their Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> could not but forſee that this Practice of going in to his Maid, which is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61505:18"/> unpreſidented in this Nation, would admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter cauſe of Scandal; and this it became one of his Character to avoid above all Men; If his Maids Beauty tempted him, it was in his Power to have rid himſelf of that Tentation: But to be plain with him, his Caſe has all the ſuſpicious Circumſtances Imaginable, to make the World believe that he was Acted by down-Right Luſt in this matter, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once engaged, now he would defend it, Anſwerable to the Practiſe of that <hi>Infamous German Enthuſiaſt,</hi> John <hi>of</hi> Leyden, <hi>who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obſerved to go into his Maids bed, did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon maintain the Doctrine of Poligamy; and the like unclean Practice engaged the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> Mahomet, <hi>in the Defence of the like unclean Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> owns, <hi>That his Wife and Sons accuſe him of former Incontinency;</hi> and the Truth on't is, his Practice and Principles, both being conſidered, there's no great Reaſon to doubt, but their Accuſation might be true. If he owns his Incontinency now when Aged, It's probable he was more ſo Twenty Years ago: If the deſertion of a beloved Wife, the Rebellion and Apoſtacy of his Sons, the Common danger which all Men at that time thought impending over the Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was a Miniſter, the Dignity of his Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the Scandal of the World could not keep him from his Maids Bed Ten Years ago, What can be thought ſufficient to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61505:18"/> have reſtrain'd him from ſuch like Practiſes Twenty Years ago?</p>
            <p n="4">4. If there was no ſuch unlawful Dalliance betwixt Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> and his Maid, while his Wife Cohabited with him, It's much that his Maid was ſo ſoon brought over to receive another Womans Husband into her Bed, and indeed one would think that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> at that time, ſhould have had ſo much trouble upon him on the Account of his Wife and Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As above, that he ſhould have had little Inclination or leaſure for a New Courtſhip, if the Familiarity had <hi>not been Contracted before.</hi> So much for the Cauſes to ſuſpect, that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> was guilty of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Incontinence in this matter.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider the pretended Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity he ſays he lay under. <hi>Durum telum Neceſſitas,</hi> Neceſſity is indeed an Irreſiſtible Weapon, but many times we make a Neceſſity to our ſelves when God makes none, and ſuch, I am affraid Mr. <hi>Butlers</hi> Neceſſity will be found.</p>
            <p>His Neceſſity proceeded meerly from his Incontinence as he owns himſelf, but we hear nothing either of Spiritual or Temporal means us'd by him to remove this Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence; Had he faſted, watched, prayed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved his Maid out of his ſight, taken the advice of Phyſicians, open'd a Vein fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, Bath'd in cold Water often, and been aſſiduous in the Work of his Calling as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and yet found his Incontinence too
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61505:19"/> hard for him after all, there would have been ſome juſtifiable Pretence for his Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but we find nothing of this done, and therefore the Neceſſity is of his own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> had found his <hi>Pruritus Carnis</hi> or Incontinence unconquerable, after the uſe of theſe, or ſuch like Means as above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, had it not been better for him to have reconciled his Wife to him, by reſtoring his Popiſh Son to the Right of Inheritance, which he pretends to be the cauſe of her deſerting him, then to take his Maid into his Bed; The former he knows, no Body would have blam'd as Criminal, whereas he could not but know, that the latter would be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Scandalous.</p>
            <p>Or if this had not been Practicable, why did not he ſue for a Divorce from his Wife upon thoſe juſt ſuſpicions of Incontinence, he charges her with by turns, <hi>p.</hi> 4. of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Reader? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And likewiſe upon the Account of her Deſertion which he ſo much inſiſts upon? Had he done this in a Legal manner, and found all the Doors of ordinary Juſtice ſhut againſt him, then he might have had recourſe to extraordinary Methods; But we don't find that he did any thing like it, ſo that his excuſe of <hi>Poperies being poſſeſs'd of the Supreme Seat, and that the High Commiſſioners ſuperſeded all other Courts, and Acted in favour of Perſons Popiſhly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd, is a meer Subterfuge, to cheat his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:61505:19"/> 
               <hi>and gull the World.</hi> This I am ſure he will find a Dilemma, that had he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to reconcile his Wife, by reſtoring his Popiſh Son to his Right of Inheritance, he would have herein been favour'd by the Court, as he owns himſelf, and that he was willing to have retain'd his Wife, if ſhe had been willing to have ſtaid with him; he has declar'd it, when he ſays that he ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited her to his Bed for above a Twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>month. But we don't ſo much as find that he made any Application to the Ordinary Courts in that Caſe, ſo that he Arraigns their Juſtice without having made Tryal of it. It's well enough known to the World that the then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Biſhops, did then oppoſe the Proceedings of the Court in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, ſuch as the publiſhing of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation for Liberty of Conſcience to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and turning out the Fellows of Colledges: So that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> had no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to decline Application to the Court of Arches for Remedy in his Caſe; nor is there any Reaſon to think but the High-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Court, wherein there were three Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> might have done him Juſtice, if he had applied to them in a Caſe ſo plain, as he alledges his to have been.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing that both thoſe Courts had been over-ruled by the Influence of Father <hi>Peters,</hi> and others, who then govern'd at
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61505:20"/> 
               <hi>Whitehall,</hi> what hinder'd Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome of his Brethren of the Clergy, or other Credible Witneſſes with him, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, to exhort his Wife, and to declare to her, that if ſhe did not return to her Duty, he would look upon their Marriage as Diſſolv'd, and provide for himſelf accordingly. If ſhe had, after all this, continued Obſtinate, why might not Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> have taken his Maid with him, and before his Brethren of the Miniſtry, or ſome Juſtices of the Peace, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, that his Wife had deſerted him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Lawful Cauſe, and would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to her Duty; that he had applied to all the Ordinary Courts of Juſtice, but could have no Remedy; and therefore being under a Neceſſity, either of burning, or taking ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Woman into his Bed, he was reſolv'd to live with his Maid, as Man and Wife? Had Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> done ſo, and made it appear to the World, that his Wife had no juſt Cauſe to deſert him, there are few Caſuiſts ſo Rigid, as to have condemn'd him, either as a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinary or Adulterer; every Body would have excus'd the want of due Formalities in ſuch a Caſe, and his Practice would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven no juſt Scandal to others, no more than did that of the Marquis of <hi>Vicum,</hi> which we ſhall have occaſion to touch upon by and by. Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> owns that his Marriage with his Wife was not altogether formal, and yet he made no Scruple to take her to his Bed; and therefore we have no Reaſon to think
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61505:20"/> that he ſhould have ſcrupled the doing of this as aboveſaid, had all things been fair and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; and if he had dreaded the anger of the Government, he might have retir'd to <hi>Holland</hi> as he did afterward. But inſtead of this, if we may believe his Wife, as quoted by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>p:</hi> 18. ſhe accuſes him of ſaying, <hi>That he had another Woman with Child, for which ſhe relinquiſh'd him, and offers to prove his having ſaid ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Circumſtances are ſo ſcandalous, that it plainly appears the Matter ought to have been Examined by Judges Competent: but it would ſeem Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> and his Maid were in too much haſte for that, or indeed to ſtay in the Kingdom, ſeeing they went over to <hi>Holland,</hi> where ſhe brought him forth a Daughter, as he owns himſelf.</p>
            <p>I come next to conſider Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for Defence of his Practice: 1. He quotes 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 15. where the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>But if the unbelieving depart, let him depart: A brother or a ſiſter is not in bondage in ſuch Caſes. In this Caſe therefore, ſays Mr.</hi> Butler, <hi>a man's own Conſcience was a good Judge, at leaſt until contrary matters could be proved before ae Competent Judge, and the Teſtimony of Holy Writ was a ſufficient Law for Conſcience to be guided by, and this without the aſſiſtance of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backt by Authority in a Caſe where an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative ſentence could not be had, as it was in St.</hi> Pauls <hi>time: Wherein the Magiſtracy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether Paganiſh, no ſuch ſentence was</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61505:21"/> 
               <hi>required as needful; and as in the Marqueſs of</hi> Vicums <hi>Caſe, wherein the ſupreme Authority being Popiſh, he married again without ſuch a ſentence. 'Tis true indeed, he had a Sentence by Authority from the Syndick of</hi> Geneva, <hi>but that was as much as juſt nothing, for firſt, that Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dick had no Authority to ſummon his Wife to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at their Court, ſhe being not under their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, and ſecondly, being a lay Power ſet up of their own accord without Power from God, or his Word, had not ſo much Power as the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the</hi> Marqueſs <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer. 1. That Mr. <hi>Butlers</hi> Caſe and that put by the Apoſtle are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; the Apoſtle ſpeaks of an Unbelievers deſerting a Believer out of an hatred to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; but Mr. <hi>Butlers</hi> Wife was of the ſame Religion with himſelf, ſo that he ought to have been backt with the Authority of the Church, whereof they were both Members before he had gone into his Maids Bed. This is the Opinion of <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Sclaterus</hi> upon the place who ſay, <hi>Lex Chriſti de Chriſtianae diſciplinae Conſortibus agit, quos propius Vinculum connectit, &amp; apud quos ſi quod aberratum eſt, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilis eſt ſanatio per Eccleſiae Authoritatem,</hi> i. e. The Law of Chriſt ſpeaks of thoſe who are partakers of the Chriſtian Diſcipline, and own'd by a nearer Tie, and who if they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any Error, the cure is eaſy by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church; but we don't find that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> ſought any ſuch Remedy, but ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinely neglected it under a pretence it could
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61505:21"/> not be had. (2.) Mr. <hi>Butlers</hi> Caſe differs alſo in this, That we had Chriſtian Magiſtrates, to whom he might have appeal'd in this Caſe, which it does not appear he did. Nor will it follow, that becauſe the Apoſtle ſays the Believer was at Liberty in Caſe of the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers deſerting, that therefore they were at liberty to take another into their Bed, without acquainting both the Church and the Magiſtrate with it; It was a General Rule to all Chriſtians, to give no Offence neither to <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Gentile,</hi> nor to the Church of God, and therefore it is not ſuppoſeable, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were referred to the dictates of their own Private Conſcience in the Caſe of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage after deſertion, tho they might reſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and without any further trouble upon the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, as to the cauſe of deſertion, <hi>viz.</hi> That it was from an hatred to their Religion, but Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> knows that his Wife accuſes him of another Cauſe, <hi>Viz.</hi> The defiling of her Bed.</p>
            <p>Then as to the <hi>Marquis</hi> of <hi>Vicums</hi> Caſe, it is alſo quite different; every one that knows the Story of the Famous <hi>Galeacius Caracciolus,</hi> knows that he fled out of <hi>Italy</hi> upon the Account of his Religion; that his Lady would neither follow him, nor admit him to her Bed, when by the Interceſſion of his Great Friends he procur'd leave to return for a time, her Prieſts having prevail'd with her to the contrary, ſo that he was forced to return without her, and lived ſeveral Years unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61505:22"/> and unblameable at <hi>Geneva,</hi> without getting into any Womans Bed in little more than a Years time, and at laſt by the conſent, not only of the Church of <hi>Geneva,</hi> but of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proteſtant Churches, and the approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Supreme Government where he lived, he married a Godly Woman not in a private manner, but in the View of the World; for it's only the deeds of darkneſs that are afraid of the Light. As to Mr. <hi>Butlers</hi> falling foul upon the Government of <hi>Geneva,</hi> as having no Power from God and his Word, he only diſcovers that he is as bad a Politician as a Divine, and a Caſuiſt of no Value. That little Common-wealth had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, ſince any thing was known of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of thoſe Parts, a Supreme Government of her own, ſometimes by a Count, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times under the Protection of the Emperor, and when the Empire was Diſtracted by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine Wars, ſhe had Recourſe to her own Biſhops who were at that time Powerful, and their Biſhops being embroil'd afterwards with the Counts of <hi>Savoy,</hi> ſhe was forc'd to ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle with the ſucceeding Dukes of <hi>Savoy</hi> for her liberty, and by Allying her ſelf with ſome of the <hi>Swiſs Cantons,</hi> brought the ſaid Dukes to Renounce their Pretenſions and at laſt by the Reformation got Rid of the Yoke of her Biſhops who oppos'd it; ſince which time the Soveraign Authority remains in her Magiſtrates and Senate, ſo that Mr. <hi>Butlers</hi> Reflection upon that Government, as wanting
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61505:22"/> Power to Authorize the Marriage of the Marquis of <hi>Vicum,</hi> then their Subject, ſavours as much of the exploded Doctrine of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtance, as his getting into his Maid's Bed ſavours of Incontinence; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what the Marquis of <hi>Vicum</hi> did in a Publick Manner, with the Conſent of all the Proteſtant Churches in thoſe Parts, and by the Authority of that which was, and is the Supreme Government, where he liv'd, is no Defence for Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Practice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Knowledge or Conſent of Church or State, or taking the Advice of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the Clergy of his Dioceſs. It is alſo to be obſerv'd, that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> diſcovers a very low Opinion of the Church, whereof he pretends to be a Miniſter, when he thought they would not have done him Juſtice, or at leaſt declared that he had Juſtice on his ſide, had his Caſe appear'd ſo clear to them, as he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges it is; but it's rather to be ſuppos'd that he diſtruſted his Cauſe, and therefore durſt not Appeal to them.</p>
            <p>I come next to conſider his Quotations from Divines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which may ſerve to amuſe one at firſt View, but can never juſtifie him in the Thoughts of a Judicious Reader, they being all of them wreſted, or nothing to his Purpoſe, or elſe directly againſt him.</p>
            <p>The firſt he quotes is <hi>Diodati</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 15. but that Author is againſt him, ſor he ſpeaks of a convenient time allow'd, and all poſſible and reaſonable Remedies uſed to reduce the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61505:23"/> Unbelieving Deſerter, before the Marriage can be diſſolved; but Mrs. <hi>Butler</hi> was no Unbeliever, nor did Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> uſe all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and reaſonable Remedies to reduce her; neither is the Caſe of her Deſertion uncontrovertible; ſhe alledges that ſhe has Divorced her ſelf, becauſe of Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Adultery.</p>
            <p>The next is <hi>Wollebius, Compend. Theolog. Cap. 11. Fol.</hi> 245. who only, Says that Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and malicious Deſertion make a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce; but not one word of the Deſerted Perſons taking another Woman, without proving the Deſertion, or asking the Conſent of Church and State.</p>
            <p>The third is <hi>Amandus Polanus, de Divortio,</hi> for which he aſſigns only two Cauſes, <hi>Viz.</hi> Adultery, and Unjuſt Deſertion; but Mrs. <hi>Butler</hi> ſays ſhe had juſt Cauſe. The laſt part of this Quotation is directly againſt Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> viz. <hi>Sed ſi perſona accuſans hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte vixit &amp; petit ferri ſententiam pronuncietur hoc modo cum perſona quae deliquit ſuo Scelere, diſſolverit Conjugium, Jude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Authoritate Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelii perſonam Innocentem Pronunciat eſſe Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram.</hi> i. e. But if the Complainant or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer have liv'd honeſtly, and demands Jugd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let it be pronounced in this manner; ſeeing the offending Perſon hath diſſolv'd the Marriage by her own Crime, the Judge, by the Authority of the Goſpel, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the Innocent Perſon to be free, and expreſly grants him Liberty, piouſly to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61505:23"/> Contract another Marriage, according to his own Conſcience. Now it's plain that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> is accus'd by his Wife of living diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſtly; ſo that this Matter ought to have been clear'd, before the Judge could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce any ſuch Sentence.</p>
            <p>In the next place it is plain, that <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Polanus</hi> is of Opinion, That ſuch a thing ought to be Judicially done, and in open Court, whereas there was no ſuch Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment demanded, nor Proceſs made by Mr. <hi>Butler;</hi> ſo that here's his own Evidence turn'd upon him.</p>
            <p>His Quotations from <hi>Muſculus</hi> upon the 5th. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> where he aſſigns Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and Deſertion, as the Cauſes of Divorce, are nothing to his Purpoſe; he does not ſay that the Matter ought not to be legally determin'd, or that the deſerted Perſon may Marry again without ſuch Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>The paſſage of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 5. is to the ſame purpoſe, and favours him not one whit.</p>
            <p>The like, that of <hi>Bucanus, Inſtitut. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae.</hi> Nor is he any thing more favour'd by that Author, <hi>Locus</hi> 13. Sect. 29. where he ſays in anſwer to the Queſtion, <hi>Quid ſi Magiſtratus officium Negligat.</hi> What if the Magiſtrate neglect his Duty? <hi>Valeat pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum Apoſtolicum ad Titum 3. 10. Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum hominem, Ergo &amp; Atheum, Apoſtatum &amp; Blaſphemum, poſt una<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Alteram correctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:61505:24"/> 
               <hi>devita:</hi>] That is, let the Apoſtles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to <hi>Titus</hi> take place, <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. 10. A Man that is an Heretick, Apoſtate, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, after the firſt and ſecond Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, reject or avoid; which Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly and falſly tranſlates, That if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate neglect his Office, the Innocent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is free to Marry an Innocent Woman, without his Sentence, whereas <hi>Bucanus</hi> ſays only, <hi>That the Believer may as freely reject the deſerting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliever in ſuch a Caſe, as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ought to do an Heretick;</hi> but ſuppoſe it were otherwiſe, he is ſtill againſt Mr. <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> in that he ſuppoſes Application ought to be made to the Magiſtrate, who cannot properly be ſaid to neglect what is never brought before him, as it is evident Mr. <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> never did; for his Wife, and not he, is the Complainant.</p>
            <p>His other Quotations are all to the ſame Purpoſe, not one of them ſpeaks one word of allowing the Deſerted Perſon to marry again, without Application made to a Competent Judge, which were, indeed, to ſubvert all Order and Government; for tho the Caſe be plain by the Law of God and Man, <hi>that a Murderer ought to be put to Death,</hi> and <hi>That an Adulterer may be divorced,</hi> and the Innocent Party lawfully marry again; yet no Man in his right Wit did ever allow, that a private Man, on his own Authority, ſhould put a Murderer to Death, or Divorce his Wife, and marry another; for all the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61505:24"/> Laws of God and Men, tho never ſo poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive require a Legal and Publick Execution and due Enquiry into the Matter of Fact, ſo that what Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> advances, <hi>p. 17. That becauſe the Text ſaith, If ſhe will depart let her go, there needs no ſentence of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate in the Caſe, will conclude as much againſt the need of the Magiſtrates ſentence in Caſe of Murder, becauſe the Text ſays, Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſheds Mans blood, by Man ſhall his blood be ſhed;</hi> And the like in all other Crimes. Otherwiſe according to this Principle, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man may be Judge, Jury, and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner in his own Caſe, which would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately deſtroy all Humane Society; ſuch are the profound Politicks of our Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binary Caſuiſt, being directly contrary to the procedure of the Almighty himſelf, who tho our firſt Parents were convicted by his Omniſcience and their our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yet He did not proceed to ſentence againſt them, till the Matter was proved by their own Confeſſion.</p>
            <p>I come next to conſider what our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor offers in defence of that he calls, <hi>A Lawful Concubinage in a Caſe of a neceſſity, wherein Lawful Marriage conveniently or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly cannot be obtain'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I had time to examine his Propoſition Narrowly, it were no hard matter to prove it a Rhapſody of Contradictions or down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Bulls;</hi> for there can be no ſuch thing as a <hi>Lawful Concubinage,</hi> nor any caſe almoſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61505:25"/> wherein <hi>Lawful arriage is not poſſible to be obtain'd;</hi> but I paſs that at preſent, and come to his inſtance, by which he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make Good this Monſtrous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. The firſt is, that of himſelf, and his firſt Wife, <hi>Martha Perkins,</hi> who, <hi>p.</hi> 21. he ſays, liv'd almoſt Forty Years together in Concubinage. Now to <hi>Live in Concubinage with a Wife is at beſt but an Iriſh ſort of Engliſh;</hi> but we ſhall let that alone and come to his Reaſon, which is, becauſe they were not Married directly according to the Cuſtom of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Miniſter having made ſome blunders and miſtakes; And yet <hi>p.</hi> 4. he own'd that ſhe was his Lawful Wife, ſo that here ſhe's both a <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Wife, and a Concubine at the ſame time:</hi> Then a little lower, becauſe he would be ſure to have Company enough, he ſays, <hi>That all thoſe Thouſands of Marriages that were made from the Rupture betwixt King</hi> Charles I. <hi>and his Parliament, to the time of</hi> Charles II's. <hi>Reſtoration, by Juſtices, Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Were all of them but meer Concubinage,</hi> and that thoſe Marriages were as much illegal as thoſe, without any Ceremony at all, till they were all made good by the Act of Indemnity of the 12th <hi>Car.</hi> 2. But then at the Foot of the Page he ſpoils all again, by ſaying, <hi>That according to the Holy Writ, there's no more Ceremony requir'd, but conſent on both Parts, before Witneſs ſufficient, and bedding together, according to</hi> Exod. 12.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61505:25"/> 26. I ſuppoſe he would have ſaid, <hi>Deut: 22. 16.) Without any preſence neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of either Magiſtrate or Prieſt.</hi> And ſo now he deals alike, both with his Brethren the Prieſts and the Juſtices of Peace, for there was neither t' one nor t' other preſent to ſee our Author go to Bed with his Maid, after <hi>Forty Years Concubinage with his Wife;</hi> So that he has ſpent a great deal of pains to prove that which no body ever doubted, that theſe Marriages may be good in the ſight of God, that are not ſuch according to the Laws of ſome Kings and Countreys. But the myſtery lies in the Application and Conſequence, <hi>Viz. That his Marriage, or rather Concubinage with his Maid, is Lawful in the ſight of God, tho not according to the Laws of the Land.</hi> But now I muſt beg his leave to ſhew him the difference of the Caſe. At that time there was a Law, or at leaſt a Power enjoining Marriages by Juſtices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And forbidding Marriage ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Book of Common Prayer, on pain of Forty Shillings for each offence, as he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 2. and Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> is ſo good a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the <hi>True Church of England,</hi> that he aſſerts thoſe Marriages by Juſtices may be good, ſetting aſide the Statutes and Laws of this Realm. But there was no Power nor Law allowing Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> or any Man to go to his Maids Bed and live with her as his Wife; (his other Wife being ſtill alive) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out application either to Magiſtracy or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61505:26"/> or the Preſence of any Witneſſes for ought that appears. And becauſe I perceive he is much for Clandeſtine Marriages, I muſt refer him to his dearly beloved <hi>Old-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> where he will find <hi>Ruth,</hi> Chap. 4. Ver. 9. That <hi>Boaz</hi>'s Marriage with <hi>Ruth</hi> was ſolemniz'd in the Preſence of the Elders; who, together with the People, pray'd for a Bleſſing upon 'em; and <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 16. he will alſo find that the Tryal of the Brides Virginity was to be made, by producing the Tokens of it before the Elders, which ſhews, that the <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> Marriages were Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and that the Solemnization and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of them depended on the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Magiſtrate, whereas Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> conſulted them in neither Caſe.</p>
            <p>Our Author in the next place, <hi>p. 22. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that God did plainly allow of a Lawful Concubinage, or Additional Wives for the Bed, for Iſſues ſake; the Iſſue whereof are no where term'd Baſtards, either in Old or New Teſtament, but upon all Occaſions in caſe of Heirs Male, wanting by the proper Wife, the Sons of Concubinage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Heirs; thus</hi> Iſhmael, <hi>Son of</hi> Abraham, <hi>by his Maid-Servant, ſhould have been Heir, if</hi> Iſaac <hi>had not been born of</hi> Sarah, Gen. 17. 18. <hi>And thus</hi> Rehoboam, <hi>Son of</hi> Solomon, <hi>by</hi> Naamah, <hi>a meer Concubine, was his Heir unto his Throne, for that he had no Son by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> proper Wife; yea, tho Daughters he had ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. And thus</hi> Jepthah, <hi>Son of</hi> Gilead, <hi>by a</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:61505:26"/> 
               <hi>Stranger, or a meer Concubine, became the Prince of the People before any of his Brethren, born of the lawful Wife, becauſe of his Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties above any of 'em;</hi> Judges 11. 2. 11. <hi>which had he been a Baſtard, could not have been; For a Baſtard might not enter into any Office in the Church, to become ſo much as a Conſtable or Church warden, much leſs a King or a Judge,</hi> Deut. 23. 2. <hi>but was to remain a Slave, equal to the</hi> Gibeonites, <hi>a Hewer of Wood, and a Drawer of Water: And at this rate none were eſteem'd Baſtards, but Children, begotten in Adultery or Whoredome, of another Man's Wife, or of a Common Whore, and ſuch could not inherit. Inceſt was a foul Sin, and yet the Children, born of Inceſt, did inherit, and were not reputed Baſtards; as</hi> Pharez, <hi>Son of</hi> Judah, <hi>by his Son's Widow, and</hi> Janna, <hi>Son of</hi> Joſeph Arſes, <hi>by his Neece; Both which were Heirs in the Genealogy of our Saviour, and therefore no Baſtards: But the Pope made Baſtards of ſuch, which by God's Laws are reputed well-born; and from the Pope our Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute-Laws ſtill keep up the Practiſe, declaring all Children to be Baſtards which are born out of Marriage; ſo as Children begot out of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, was a Sin againſt the King's Laws and Statutes, and yet no Sin againſt God's Law.</hi> Theſe are our Author's own Words, becauſe I would give him fair Play, and let his Arguments appear in their native Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Strength.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:61505:27"/>
            <p>I anſwer, <hi>Had God allowed of Additional Wives for Iſſue ſake, we ſhould have it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where mention'd in Holy Writ, and let our Author produce a Text for it if he can.</hi> If God allow'd Additional Wives, how came it that he made but one for <hi>Adam,</hi> and that one too, we have God's own Word for it was a <hi>Meet-help, Gen.</hi> 18. 29. which could not be true, if more Wives than one were neceſſary for one Man. The Prophet <hi>Malachi, c.</hi> 2. 15. when he Expoſtulates with the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for dealing treacherouſly with the Wife of their Youth, and reproves them for their Divorces, argues in the ſame manner, <hi>viz. Did he not make one, yet had he the Reſidue of the Spirit, and wherefore one? That he might ſeek a Godly Seed, therefore take heed to your Spirit, and let none deal treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly againſt the Wife of his Youth;</hi> which the Criticks Paraphraſe or Interpret thus: <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non unam duntaxat Conjugem Adamo fecit, non plures uxores uni viro. Revocat hic Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos ad Puram conjugii Naturam &amp; primam Inſtitutionem:</hi> And again, <hi>Quamvis plures ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas creare poſſit quas inderet pluribus Mulieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Adamo jungendis neque enim defecit eum in una Muliere Spiritus, id autem quum non fecerit Argumento hoc certe eſt, quod nolit uni viro plures uxores jungi. Quorſum autem unum, nempe unum illum hominem conſtantem ex viro &amp; Muliere, hoc unice Scilicet agebat, ut habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Legitimam Sobolem; Oſtendit enim ſpurios</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:61505:27"/> 
               <hi>fore qui ex Polygamia Naſeentur, quia non Gig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntur Secundum Dei Inſtitutionem. Attenti ſitis igitur ad Cavendum ne perſide agatis, vel Spiritu (hoc eſt animo) veſtro, ne datam fidem primae uxori violetis alia ſuperinducta, i. e.</hi> 
               <q>Did he not make one Wife for <hi>Adam,</hi> and not divers Wives for one Man? Here he Recalls them to the pure Nature of <hi>Wedlock,</hi> and firſt <hi>Inſtitution of Marriage.</hi> Altho he could have created more Souls, to put into more Women, to be joyn'd to <hi>Adam;</hi> for the Life that he breath'd into <hi>Eve,</hi> he could have breathed into more; but whereas he did not do ſo; It is certainly an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he would not have one Man to have more Wives than one. And why did he make one, that is to ſay, one Man, conſiſting of Male and Female? On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for this end, that there might be a Lawful Off-ſpring; by which he ſhews, that the Children, born of <hi>Polygamy,</hi> ſhould be ſpurious, becauſe not begot according to the Inſtitution of God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed, watch over your Spirits, that you don't ſo much, as in your Mind, violate the Troth, which you have pligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your firſt Wife, by bringing in another upon her.</q> The Authors of this Expoſition are <hi>Capellus, Calvin, Piſcator, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovicus de Dieu, Menochius, Tarnovius,</hi> &amp;c. as may be ſeen in <hi>Pool's Synopſis.</hi> So that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61505:28"/> here is the Prophet <hi>Malachi,</hi> and many Divines of great Note of an Opinion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Mr. <hi>Butler, viz.</hi> that God never allowed Additional Wives, and always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the Children of <hi>Polygamy</hi> Spurious, or Baſtards. And as for our Author's Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>p. 21. That every Man was to Marry but one Woman, who was to be Lady, or Dame of the Family;</hi> I have already ſhew'd him from <hi>Lev. 18. 18. That no Man was to take a Wife to her Siſter</hi> (the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Phraſe, for two Wives together) <hi>to vex her, to uncover her Nrkedneſs, beſides the other in her Life time.</hi> Now the Reaſon of the Wifes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vex'd, is plainly ſaid to be the Unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of the others Nakedneſs; and Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> knows by Experience, that the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of a Concubines Nakedneſs vexes his Wife; and therefore the Reaſon is as ſtrong againſt <hi>Concubines,</hi> as if they were <hi>Ladies,</hi> or <hi>Dames of the Family,</hi> as well as ſhe he calls the <hi>one Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to his Argument from <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſucceed <hi>Abraham,</hi> as his Heir, if <hi>Iſaac</hi> had not been born: It's no Argument that God approv'd <hi>Concubinage,</hi> nor does our Author find any where that God had commanded that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſhould ſucceed in that Caſe; but it's plain that he was ſent awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by God's Order; that he ſhould not partake of the Inheritance with <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 21. 10 and 12. <hi>ver.</hi> compared, becauſe he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61505:28"/> was the Son of a Bond-woman, ſo that this Inſtance makes againſt Mr. <hi>Butler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then as to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> owns that <hi>Solomon</hi> had no other Son; Beſides, the Succeſſion's being continued upon him, was by a ſpecial Decree, as appears, 1 <hi>Kin. 11. 35. To his Son will I give one Tribe, that</hi> David, <hi>my Servant, may have always a Light before me in</hi> Jeruſalem: So that this is nothing to his Purpoſe. The Kindneſs was to <hi>David,</hi> and not to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> as the Son of a Concubine; And here 'tis fit to take Notice that the Inſtance, of paſſing by <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Daughters by his proper Wife, as Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> calls her, <hi>makes againſt his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Doctrine of the Divine Right of a Lineal Succeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, as to <hi>Jepthah</hi>'s being a Judge, if our Author had but look'd to the ſecond Verſe of the 11th. Chapter of the <hi>Judges,</hi> he would find that his Brethren would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him no Part of the Inheritance, for that very Reaſon, <hi>becauſe he was the Son of a ſtrange Woman;</hi> which is plainly againſt Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> and ſhews that the Sons of Concubines were not judged to have any Right of Inheritance. But that does not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but the People might chuſe ſuch an one for a Judge, Commander or General, in time of Diſtreſs, and Diſorder, as the times of the Judges were; when every Man did what was Right in his own Eyes, there
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61505:29"/> being at that time no King in <hi>Iſrael, Judg.</hi> 21. 25. Beſides, our Author owns that <hi>Jep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thah</hi> was choſen Judge for his Abilities, and not becauſe of his Birthright.</p>
            <p>As to the Law mentioned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. 2. a Baſtard ſhall not enter into the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Lord; Commentators under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that to be meant by Children of a Common Whore. Whereas in theſe times of Ignorance, that God winked at, Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, were ſolemnly Married, and were accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſort of Wives, and the Man's Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to whom they were ſo Married; and that <hi>Jepthah</hi>'s Mother was a privare Concubine, any Man, who will conſult the Criticks, may find to have been the Opinion of <hi>Munſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and <hi>Cornelius a Lapide.</hi> But ſuppoſe it had been otherwiſe, tho God impoſes a Law upon us, he impoſes none upon himſelf, ſo that he may diſpenſe with it when he pleaſes. And if he did ſo in this Caſe, and others of the like Nature, to let thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Children ſee that he extended Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to them, notwithſtanding the Sins of their Parents, that all ſuch might not be driven to Deſpair of his Goodneſs; what ſays that in Excuſe of <hi>Polygamy?</hi>—Our Author may as well defend Inceſt from this Topick, (which yet he owns to be a foul Crime) becauſe, as he obſerves himſelf, <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez,</hi> the Inceſtuous Son of <hi>Judah,</hi> by his Daughter-in-Law <hi>Tamar,</hi> ſucceeded as Heir
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61505:29"/> to his Father, and is mention'd in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Genealogy. Who dare or can li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who hath ſaid, <hi>he will have Mercy, on whom he will have Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> Of this Opinion our Author may alſo find <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius</hi> a <hi>Lapide;</hi> And as to <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Janna,</hi> mention'd in our Saviour's Genealogy, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. It may be ſolved the ſame way. God of his Soveraign Grace chuſes and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies whom he pleaſes; nor is it any Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation upon our Saviour, that he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated unto, as well as came to ſave the chief of Sinners. <hi>Non dedignatur Chriſtus ex pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricibus &amp; Gentilibus naſci,</hi> ſay <hi>Lucas Brugenſis Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donatus &amp; Cajetan, quia venit ut utraſque ſalvaret,</hi> Chriſt did not diſdain to derive his Pedigree from ſinful Women and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> becauſe he came into the World to ſave both of 'em. So that this makes nothing at all for our Author's Purpoſe, for the ſame Argument will conclude as ſtrongly, that God approves Murder, Adultery, Inceſt, Common-Whores, and Heatheniſm; becauſe <hi>Bathſheba, Thamar, Rachel,</hi> and <hi>Ruth,</hi> are mention'd in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Genealogy, Whereas it only ſhews the exceeding Riches of God's Grace, in exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo much Compaſſion to the worſt of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. For, that <hi>Bathſheba</hi> was an Adultreſs, and became <hi>David</hi>'s Wife, by Murder, is plain; that <hi>Thamar</hi> was an Inceſtuous Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, and her Children, <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Zara,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:61505:30"/> Baſtards cannot be denied, and that <hi>Judah</hi> begot thoſe Children upon her, as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Harlot, is obvious to any one that Reads the Story; that <hi>Rahab</hi> was a Common Proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute is no leſs known, and no Body can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that <hi>Ruth</hi> was a <hi>Moabiteſs;</hi> But of all theſe we may ſay with the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. Such they were once, but at laſt were waſhed, ſanctified, and juſtified, in the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>As to his unmannerly Reflection upon our Statute Laws, that declare all Children born out of Marriage to be Baſtards, <hi>As if they were deriv'd from the Pope,</hi> Let the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment look to it; but this looks indeed like Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Politicks and Divinity. He might know that the Holy Scripture calls ſuch <hi>Baſtards,</hi> Deut. 23. 2. <hi>Quivis extra Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, conjugium natus</hi> ſays, <hi>Gerundenſis,</hi> any one born out of Lawful Marriage: And if it do not call the Children of Concubines by that Name, becauſe of the Reſpect due to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, tho unlawfully Contracted; It does not follow, but that in effect they really were ſuch. And therefore our Law which admits of no Concubinage, has reaſon to call all Children begot out of Marriage Baſtards, Whether ever the Pope had done ſo or not. Our Author knows, that the Scripture does not call <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Zara</hi> Baſtards, tho they really were ſo, as being not only Begot out of Lawful <hi>Wedlock,</hi> but in horrid Inceſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61505:30"/> 
               <hi>Judah</hi> thought he had to do with a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Harlot. And therefore his Argument from the Scriptures, not calling every one in particular, Begot in Concubinage, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlawful Manner Baſtards, has no weight at all, eſpecially ſeeing it is plain, that it calls all thoſe Begot out of <hi>Wedlock</hi> in General, by that Name.</p>
            <p>I come next to our Authors Hiſtorical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, <hi>p.</hi> 23. and 24. The firſt is the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</hi> Scotland'<hi>s Legitimation of the Sons of</hi> Robert Stuart, <hi>King of</hi> Scots, <hi>by</hi> Elizabeth Moor, <hi>his Concubine; and his being ſucceeded by</hi> John, <hi>the Eldeſt of thoſe Sons by Concubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, notwithſtanding he had Two Sons by his Lawful Wife</hi> Eupham, <hi>Daughter to the Earl of</hi> Roſſe, <hi>then living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. The Practice of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or any other Nation in this Caſe, ſuppoſe it were true as our Author lays it down, <hi>Viz.</hi> That the Reaſons moving them ſo to do, <hi>Were that ſhe had been a true Wife to him, before God in all things, excepting the deficiency of the Rites and Ceremonies of Marriage,</hi> Is no Rule to us, nor cannot warrant out Conſcienees. But our Author may pleaſe to know that there have been diſcoveries made ſince, which make it highly probable, that <hi>Robert Stuart</hi> was Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Elizabeth Moor,</hi> whilſt he was a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Man, tho he thought fit for Reaſons of State to conceal it when he came to the Crown, and this is urg'd by Sir <hi>Geo. Macken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:61505:31"/> and others, in Defence of the Royal Line of <hi>Scotland.</hi> But ſuppoſing it were not ſo, his Sons by <hi>Elizabeth Moor,</hi> were Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by the Parliament of that Kingdom, which formerly was the Supreme Power of that Nation; and if we may believe their Hiſtories, gave Laws to their Kings but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd none from them: So that they ſet up, Dethron'd, and Puniſh'd their Kings, as they thought fit. A plain inſtance of this, is that Letter to the Pope from the States of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> I. as is to be ſeen in Dr. <hi>Burnets</hi> Hiſtory of the Reformation, <hi>Wherein they tell him that they had Dethron'd</hi> John Baliol, <hi>for ſuch and ſuch Cauſes, and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> Robert Bruce, <hi>whom they would alſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne if he committed the like Miſdemeanours.</hi> They afterwards ſettled the Succeſſion upon the ſaid <hi>Bruces</hi> Brother and his Iſſue, failing the Kings own Male Iſſue, tho he had a Daughter then living, who was Mother to this very <hi>Robert Stuart; So that in thoſe days they believ'd nothing of the Divine Right of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Lineal Succeſſion.</hi> They afterwards made an Act in <hi>Robert Bruces</hi> time, <hi>that in Caſe of any diſpute about the Succeſſion, it ſhould be decided by the Parliament, and the King of</hi> France <hi>by his League was oblig'd to aſſiſt him with Arms, to whom they adjudg'd the Crown.</hi> After King <hi>James</hi> the Third was ſlain in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle near <hi>Sterlin,</hi> the firſt Parliament held by his Son, enacted, <hi>That ſuch as fell on the</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:61505:31"/> 
               <hi>King's ſide, were Lawfully ſlain, as Enemies to the Publick, not ſo much as excepting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: And that thoſe who fought againſt him, were no way Culpable.</hi> Nay, this preſent Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> declar'd, that the <hi>Late King James had forfeited their Crown,</hi> and did not trouble themſelves to debate whether he had abdicated or not. So that to argue from an Act of Parliament in <hi>Scotland,</hi> relating to their Government, to a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Caſe, like that of our Authors, is to argue, <hi>de Genere in Genus,</hi> quite Forraign to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and ſhews him to be as Ignorant of the Laws of Argument, as undeſerving of the Character of a true Church of <hi>England-Man,</hi> to take Preſidents from a Countrey who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had a Mortal hatred to paſſive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: But beſides in admitting the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Race to this Crown; our Anceſtors did not trouble themſelves with the Queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were Lawfully begot or not? But whether King <hi>James</hi> I. was deſcended in the Eye of the Law from our <hi>Hen.</hi> VIIth? For if we may believe ſome of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Hiſtorians, there was Reaſon enough to queſtion that Princes Birth, without going any further back. But it ſeems our Anceſtors were as much refolv'd to have him for their King as the Proteſtant <hi>Scots</hi> were, of whom the Earl of <hi>Glencarn,</hi> then one of the chief, is quoted by ſome of their Writers for ſaying to his Mother, when ſhe to avoid being Dethron'd,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61505:32"/> her ſelf, gave plain enough hints that he was none of the moſt Lawful Iſſue, <hi>They knew that if his Stone Horſe had begot him he ſhould be King of Scots:</hi> They conſidered him as born in Lawful <hi>Wedlock,</hi> without troubling themſelves to enquire whether he was Lawfully begot, and tho they knew, they had no great reaſon to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire her Chaſtity, they knew alſo that ſhe had too much Intereſt to ſay, that he was ſpurious to be believed. The ſame Anſwer is enough to his other Inſtances of <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror and <hi>Henry</hi> VIIth. Their Claims were Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riz'd by Parliaments, who in Extraordinary Caſes muſt conſult the Publick welfare (for <hi>Salus Populi ſuprema lex,</hi> is a Maxim that will hold Eternally true) and are not to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the Notions of Clergy-Men, no more then our Late Parliaments were by their falſe Notions of Paſſive obedience, when they ſettled the Crown upon King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary, &amp;c.</hi> Moreover, ſeeing this Law about the Imploying of Baſtards in places of Authority was not giv'n to us, and alſo diſpens'd with by the <hi>Jews,</hi> to whom it was giv'n, there's no Reaſon that any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Nation ſhould look upon themſelves as oblig'd by it, when the welfare of the State does indiſpenſibly require the ſetting up of ſuch an one, ſo that all our Authors Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from hence to prove Concubinage Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, vaniſh into ſmoak. Beſides <hi>Bonfrerius</hi> and <hi>Oleaſter</hi> are of Opinion, that it was For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Baſtards, and not thoſe of their own
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61505:32"/> People that were here prohibited, becauſe <hi>Pharez</hi> tho a Baſtard was admitted into the Congregation, and <hi>Jepthah,</hi> &amp;c. Made a Judge, and the Reaſon of the prohibition, Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators think to be, that Baſtards were Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally accounted Vile in the Eyes of their own People, neglected in their Education, and ſo unfit for Government.</p>
            <p>Our Authors next Argument, <hi>Of Prieſts Marriage being formerly cried down, but now accounted Lawful is nothing to the purpoſe;</hi> The Lawfulneſs of that was always clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable from the Scriptures, but ſo was not that of Concubinage.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> P. 27. Says, <hi>I am of Opinion we may find ſome other matters ſtill ſpoken againſt that, may upon ſerious conſideration be found as Innocent and Holy as that</hi> (meaning Prieſts Marriage) <hi>is at this day, and among other things, I propoſe a Lawful Concubinage as in ſome Caſes it may be required, and to this purpoſe it is Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the New Teſtament,</hi> Heb. 13. 4. <hi>That Marriage is Honourable in all, and the Bed unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, but Whoremongers and Adulterers God will Judge. Then he argues, that by Bed undefil'd is meant ſome other Bed different from the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage Bed, becauſe the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a Copulative, which Couples ſentences of a diſtinct ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for that which is the ſame thing in ſenſe with that which went before needs no Bond of Copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for if the Author had intended one and the ſame thing, by theſe words he would have ſaid Marriage (being) or which is a Bed undefil'd.</hi> I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61505:33"/> Anſwer, This Poor Man is put to miſerable ſhifts, to lull his own Conſcience aſleep, and to gull thoſe of others, 'twill grant him that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Couples ſentences of different ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here, and that <hi>Marriage and Bed undefil'd are different things,</hi> but how will that prove, that there's any other Bed betwixt a Man and a Woman undefil'd except the Marriage Bed? Is it not plain, that the Bed may be defil'd by Married Perſons? Mrs. <hi>Butler ſays our Author defil'd her Bed while ſhe was Married to him.</hi> So that tho Marriage be Honourable, that does not ſay, but Married Perſons may Diſhonour themſelves by defiling the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Bed, which by God and Man is always accounted more Diſhonourable then Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt Perſons unmarried, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles ſenſe is plain, <hi>Marriage is Honourable, and to keep the Marriage Bed unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd is Honourable, but thoſe that commit Fornication, and thoſe that Defile the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage bed by Adultery, God will Judge,</hi> That this is the plain meaning of the Text, may be evinc'd thus, the Apoſtle propoſes Marriage as Honourable in oppoſition to Fornication, which is Leudneſs betwixt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married Perſons; therefore ſays the Apoſtle Marriage is Honourable, but God will Judge Fornicators. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is ſays <hi>Grotius, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere utentes extra Conjugium,</hi> unmarried Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who lie together, and the Bed undefil'd is Honourable, continues the Apoſtle, but God will Judge Adulterers; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> That is,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61505:33"/> ſuch as Defile the Marriage-Bed, unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Perſons have none to Defile. Beſides, there may be a Defiling of the Marriage Bed, even betwixt Married Perſons, by Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and the Immoderate Uſe of it.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> owns <hi>P.</hi> 8. that he himſelf was guilty of Incontinence, with the Complainant <hi>Martha,</hi> whileſt his Wife, which certainly was a Defiling of the Marriage Bed. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſays upon the place, <hi>Cubile Impollutum addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ut Sciant conjugati non quidvis ſibi Liceri, ſed uſum thori Legitimi debere eſſe Moderatum ne quid alienum a Conjugij pudore &amp; Caſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia admittant.</hi> i. e. The Bed Undefiled is added, that married Perſons may know that their Liberty is not boundleſs, but that the Uſe of the Lawful Bed ought to be moderate, leſt they ſhould commit ſomething unbeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Modeſty of Wedlock, or Chaſtity; and ſo if Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> went to Bed with his Wife, during his Incontinence, when he ought to have been at Prayers in the Church, or Viſiting the Sick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it was a thing unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Wedlock and Chaſtity; ſo that here he ſees that Marriage and the Bed Unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed are things as much different, as Mr. <hi>Butler, the Husband of Martha Perkins,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Butler, not a Concubinary afterwards with Mary Tomkins,</hi> or any other Woman; or Mr. <hi>Butler in Bed with his Wife at Lawful Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Butler not in Bed with his Wife when he ſhould be Viſiting the Sick. Junius,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:61505:34"/> 
               <hi>Piſcator, Gerundenſis, Gataker, Menochius, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus,</hi> and others, do all underſtand this Word Undefiled to be meant of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage Bed tho ſome of 'em will have it to be Periphraſtical, and others Preceptive; and Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> himſelf inſtances a Caſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he owns the Word <hi>Kai</hi> to be Exegetical, or Explanatory of the thing preceeding, <hi>viz. Epheſ 1 3. Bleſſed be God, and the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> which the ſame Apoſtle writes, 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 3. Bleſſed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in which the Particle, <hi>and</hi> is Exegetical.</p>
            <p>But ſays Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> p. 28. <hi>That if we read the Words thus; Marriage, ev'n the Bed unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, is honourable: There will be a Riddle in the Caſe; for why did he make account that Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage could not be honourable, unleſs it were a Bed undefiled? No, that could not be, for Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of it ſelf is an honourable State, in all Caſes and Perſons. And again it would follow, that all Marriages are, even a Bed undefiled, which is not ſo; for there are very many Profane and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean Marriages; and therefore the Holy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor treats of a Bed undefiled, plainly diſtinct and different from a Marriage-Bed, that may truly be ſtiled a Lawful and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled Bed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is a very odd way of arguing. I have ſhew'd that there's no neceſſity of reading the Words ſo, and that moſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators take them to be ſpoke of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-Bed, but under different Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61505:34"/> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> as Defiled and Undefiled. Our Author alſo runs into Contradictions; for in one Line he ſays, <hi>Marriage is honourable in all Caſes, even, tho the Bed be not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled;</hi> and in a few Lines after ſays, <hi>There are very many Prophane and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean Marriages.</hi> Let him reconcile this if he can: As to his Q. if the Apoſtle did not account Marriage Honourable, unleſs it were a Bed Undefiled; it's downright Impertinent; Marriage is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as a Remedy for keeping the Bed Undefiled: The Apoſtle's Meaning is plain enough, that Marriage was Honourable, but it was very Diſhonourable in married Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to Defile the Marriage-Bed, either by the Immoderate Uſe of it betwixt themſelves, or by taking others into it. <hi>Calvin</hi> and others, I have quoted for the former, and for the latter, <hi>Gataker</hi> and others comment upon it thus: It is as much as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Maritalis, nulla contaminetur Macula, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterii aut ullius peccati contra fidem conjuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. i. e.</hi> Let not the Marriage-Bed be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed by any Spot, either of Adultery, or any other Crime againſt the Conjugal Vow. As to what our Author alledges, that there are many Prophane and Unclean Marriages, thoſe are none of God's Appointment, and the Apoſtle treats here only of ſuch: I do believe that his Marriage with <hi>Mary Tomkins</hi> is Prophane and Unclean, if it can be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any Marriage at all; but to be plainer
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61505:35"/> with him, there can be no ſuch thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſpeaking, as an Unclean Marriage, tho ſome Unclean Perſons may perhaps marry only for Unclean Ends. Marriage is an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ordinance of God, and can never be Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, tho many Unclean Practices may be covered under that Name; for every one that marries, does not <hi>marry in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus made it plain, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks of the <hi>Marriage Bed only,</hi> our Author's Inference, that he ſpeaks of a <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled Bed, diſtinct from a Marriage Bed,</hi> falls to the Ground of Courſe.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Butler, P.</hi> 19. has Recourſe to the Practice of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> to whom this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was writ, to prove this forc'd Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary he puts upon the Text, for which he neither does nor can quote one Expoſitor; and therefore alledges, <hi>that becauſe the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews always held a Bed of Concubinage to be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled and Honourable; that the Apoſtle must needs therefore mean Concubinage by a Bed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled.</hi> I anſwer, 1. That I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prov'd Concubinage among the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to have been contrary to the Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, tho Conniv'd at in thoſe times of Ignorance: 2. That <hi>Concubinage</hi> could not be the Apoſtle's Meaning; for our Author himſelf will own that Marriage does alſo imply a Bed Undefiled, otherwiſe it could not be Honourable; ſo that it would be Nonſence for the Apoſtle to diſtinguiſh <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:61505:35"/> from Marriage by the Words <hi>Bed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled,</hi> as if it were more properly ſo, than Marriage it ſelf, which was of Divine Inſtitution. 3. That the Apoſtle muſt not be ſuppos'd to Contradict his Maſter Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who recall'd Marriage to its firſt Inſtitution betwixt one Man and one Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at a time, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 4, 5, 6. where he ſays, <hi>They twain</hi> (not they three, four, or five) <hi>ſhall be one Fleſh;</hi> and inſtead of our Author's Aſſertion, that the Apoſtle ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves <hi>Concubinage,</hi> becauſe he wrote to the <hi>Jews,</hi> it's more probable that he reproves it, as our Saviour did their Divorces, in the 19th. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> which <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe of the Hardneſs of their Hearts, had ſuffer'd, and they thereupon thought Lawful. But our Saviour tells them <hi>that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it was not ſo;</hi> and it's as plain, that <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamy</hi> or <hi>Concubinage</hi> was not from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſo that our Saviours' Argument concludes as ſtrongly againſt thoſe, as againſt the Divorces then in Uſe amongſt the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grotius</hi> ſays, That the Apoſtle here oppoſes himſelf to that Opinion, which many of the Jewiſh Rabbies maintain'd, <hi>viz.</hi> That it was no Crime to Lie with any Woman, tho not married to her, if ſhe was not a <hi>Jeweſs,</hi> becauſe they thought <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law only reſtrain'd them as to ſuch.—Therefore he adviſes them to take heed, leſt there be any Fornicator amongſt them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 16.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61505:36"/> And in this Text propoſes Marriage as a Remedy againſt Fornication, as has been ſaid already.</p>
            <p>This Anſwer of our Saviour, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuffer'd ſuch things, becauſe of the Hardneſs of their Hearts, is ſufficient to put an end to all thoſe Cavils from the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> Inſtances. The <hi>Jews</hi> were a ſtiff necked People, which is given them in many Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as their Character; and therefore <hi>Moſes,</hi> by Divine Permiſſion, ſuffer'd thoſe things, tho he did not command them; He ſuffer'd them, to prevent greater Evils; leſt they ſhould have murder'd their Wives, or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them harſhly: 2. They were ſuffer'd, as common Laws of Nations do allow, more than is allow'd by the Laws of Religion, as is clear from this Inſtance; that in all Chriſtian Kingdoms there are Judges, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for deciding Differences betwixt Man and Man, of what Nature ſoever they may be, for preventing Oppreſſion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice; ſo that the Bench is open to trivial and frivolous Suits, as well as to thoſe that are weighty and material; yet the Practice of ſuch as go to Law upon every Occaſion, is contrary to the Apoſtle's Command, and Chriſtian Charity, as appears by 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 6. 3. They were ſuffer'd as a proper Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their Wickedneſs; for it both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted their Bodies and Eſtates, and broke the Peace of their own Families, and engaged
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61505:36"/> them in Diſcord with others. 4. This Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were given over to a Temporal Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are to a Spiritual For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: But our Saviour, the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> when he came to Redeem the World, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd Marriage again to its firſt Inſtitution, as it was in the Firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s time.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Butler P.</hi> 20. alledges, <hi>that God at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted the Legitimacy of</hi> Iſhmael'<hi>s Birth by the Bleſſing he gave him.</hi> Our Author, ſure, knows it's a Maxim in Divinity, that we muſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure God's Will by his Word, and not by his Providence. The Wiſe Man tells us, that Outward Things happen alike to the Good, and to the Bad. The Text tells us that it was for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſake that God gave <hi>Iſhmael</hi> Temporal Bleſſings, and ſo he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Eſau</hi> for <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s ſake; whence our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor may as well conclude, that God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd of that Prophane Perſon. <q>Beſides, it's plain from the Text that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was an Accurſed Perſecutor, had his Hand againſt every Man, and every Man's Hand againſt him; his Poſterity we find complain'd of <hi>Pſalm</hi> 83. amongſt other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the People of God. And as the Author of the Book, call'd <hi>God's Judgments againſt Whoring,</hi> obſerves, ſo they have continued under ſeveral Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations to this day; as <hi>Iſhmaelites, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garens, &amp;c.</hi> of which latter Name being aſham'd, as denoting their ſpurious Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61505:37"/> they aſſum'd to themſelves the Title of <hi>Saracens,</hi> as if they were <hi>Sarah</hi>'s Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring; under which they were formidable to the Chriſtian World for ſome Ages, and continue irreconcileable Enemies to the Chriſtian Religion to this day, under the name of <hi>Arabians, Turks, &amp;c.</hi> and are ſo addicted unto Uncleanneſs, that they place their chief Happineſs here and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in the Enjoyment of their Senſual Pleaſures.</q> So far was <hi>Iſhmael</hi> or his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from being truly bleſſed; To that Book I refer our Author, where he will find an Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Account of the Puniſhments, inflicted upon the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and others, for their Poligamy and Concubinage, which he will needs have <hi>to be a Bed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 30. he ſays, God allow'd of <hi>David</hi>'s Concubinage, becauſe 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 8. God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating with <hi>David,</hi> becauſe of his Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and the Murder of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſays. <hi>And I gave thee thy Maſters Houſe, and thy Maſters Wives into thy boſom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, God gave <hi>David</hi> the Poſſeſſion of of all that was <hi>Saul</hi>'s, to uſe Lawfully, but not to uſe Unlawfully, otherwiſe he muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of Inceſt, for it was not Lawful for any Man to have his Father-in-Law's Wiſe, nor does it appear that <hi>David</hi> made uſe of them as Wives. So God is ſaid to give <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Concubines to <hi>Abſalom,</hi> which will make him the Author of Inceſt, if giving
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61505:37"/> do always ſignifie approving; but the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is no more then this, that he ſuffer'd <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> to fall into that Tentation, and took his Reſtraining Grace from him, that ſo <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Sin might be puniſh'd by that of his Son. So God gave <hi>Saul</hi> into <hi>David</hi>'s Hand, yet he himſelf own'd it was not Lawful for him to kill him. The word in the Original ſignifies any Women; as <hi>Junius,</hi> and <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius a Lapide</hi> obſerve; ſo that it may be meant of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Daughters that were <hi>David</hi>'s Wives: Beſides, its plain, if he had added <hi>Saul</hi>'s Wives to thoſe that he had before, he had tranſgreſſed the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 17. againſt Kings multiplying Wives; which God would never have approved of. So that the meaning of that place ſeems to be no more, than that God amongſt other things that were <hi>Saul</hi>'s, gave him alſo his Wife's. But ſeeing it is doubtful our Author will find but little Stability in it for his Conſcience to build upon. His Inſtance from <hi>Reh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>boam</hi>'s Succeſſion in that ſame Page is anſwered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and for that from the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi>'s being order'd to take another Woman, his own being yet alive. Our Author cannot but know that <hi>Rivet,</hi> and other Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, underſtand it to be Parabolical to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent God's Love to an Adulterous an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Treacherous People: Or if otherwiſe, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſwers himſelf, when he ſays, it was by ſpecial Command from God, who may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61505:38"/> with his own Law when he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>His Inſtance of the Conception of our Saviour, p. 32. is Villainous and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. God form'd <hi>Adam</hi> out of the Duſt by his Omnipotence, and forms us in the Womb <hi>Mediante Generatione;</hi> and can his forming of our Saviour's Humane Nature there, without any ſuch <hi>Medium,</hi> any way import a Violation of Virginity? Does not the immodeſt Man know, that this was altogether Miraculous, and Propheſied of before as ſuch? <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 7. 14. Can any Man not wholly bereft of Senſe, or hardened in Impiety, compare this any way to a Bed out of Marriage? but this Mans Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous Luſt makes him flie on the Face of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 32. He will have our Saviour to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of a Bed out of Marriage as Undefiled, <hi>John</hi> 4. 10. becauſe he bleſſed the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> and her Husband or Man, with whom ſhe liv'd in Concubinage, without ſo much as reproving her for it, or order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her to diſcontinue her Courſe of Life; as our Saviour uſed to do in Sinful Caſes; as <hi>John</hi> 8. 11. and 5. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That Chriſt reprov'd her is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent enough, when he told her, that he whom ſhe then had was not her Husband; and it's plain from her own Words to her Neighbours, that ſhe was touch'd with his Reproof, when ſhe ſaid to them, that he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61505:38"/> had told her all that ever ſhe did in her Life, tho we hear of nothing elſe but this one matter. All Commentators agree that Chriſt's telling her, that he whom ſhe had now was not her Husband, was a ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof and a Check to her, for mocking him in asking for Water to quench her Thirſt, when he was ſpeaking to her of Water from the Wells of Salvation, and alſo by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to deceive him when ſhe told him, that ſhe had no Husband. By her Anſwer 'tis alſo plain that ſhe confeſſed her Crime; I perceive ſays ſhe, that thou art a Prophet, which was a direct owning of the Truth of what he ſaid. Now her Crime according to <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Lightfoot</hi> in <hi>Hora</hi> was, that ſhe had Five Husbands, from whom ſhe had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorc'd her ſelf contrary to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or had been Five times divorc'd for Adultery, and that ſhe was truly touch'd with a ſenſe of her ſin appears, In that ſhe was ſtraight way Sollicitous to know, whether ſhe Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped God in a Right manner or not. If our Author conſult <hi>Bucer, Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Melancton</hi> upon the place, he will find they were fully of this Opinion, that Chriſt by diſcourſing her, ſought an opportunity to reprove her, and that it was not in ſharper Terms, only ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, that he was unwilling to break the bruiſed Reed. That the Woman was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſenſible of her Faults, appears in this, that ſhe took ſhame to her ſelf by own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61505:39"/> them before all her fellow Citizens, that ſhe was a ſincere believer, appears from her Zealous deſire to have them made Partakers of the Grace of God, as well as her ſelf, and that ſhe broke off her impure Courſe of Life, is not to be queſtioned ſeeing it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſhe had Faith, which is an Heart purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace, but as to <hi>Her Husbands coming with her, receiving part of the Bleſſing, and having his Concubinage approv'd:</hi> It is only the Comment of our Concubinary Author, Our Saviour would never Contradict himſelf by Preaching another Doctrine to her, than he did in <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. And a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>low her ſix Husbands at once when he recall'd Marriage there, to its firſt Inſtitution betwixt one and one.</p>
            <p>I come next to conſider our Authors de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a Whoremonger, <hi>p. 33. He is ſays he, ſuch a wretch who tho allow'd to Marry, or to keep his Concubine, that is a Woman proper to himſelf provided he do not multiply Concubines, nor keep any Woman unlawfully Compaſſed unto any mans wrong, or to that Womans wrong, and uſeth her not meerly for his Luſt, but out of a pure deſire of an Holy Seed by her, yet not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with that Lawful Liberty, chuſeth rather to ſpend the Holy Seed of mankind upon Common Women, and thus expoſeth his Seed to be murdered in the Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I obſerve, our Author diſtinguiſhes betwixt Marrying and Keeping a Concubine as different things, which plainly overthrows
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61505:39"/> what he aſſerts, for our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. Speaks not one word of allowing a Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, but that they that cannot contain ſhould Marry, <hi>v.</hi> 11. 12. The Apoſtle anſwerable to this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 2, 9. Propoſes Marriage as a Remedy againſt Fornication and Incontinence, but ſpeaks not one word of a Concubine, and from thence alſo it is plain, that by Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers the Apoſtle means ſuch Perſons as are not Married, and yet make uſe of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, elſe Marriage were no proper remedy for them, which perfectly deſtroys Mr. <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> Concubinage, ſeeing the Apoſtle doth thereby Condemn all uſe of Women out of a Married State: As to what our Author ſays is allowed at <hi>Rome,</hi> and in ſome Reform'd States (tho there be none of the latter charg'd with any ſuch thing but <hi>Holland)</hi> it's no warrant for any Mans Conſcience</p>
            <p>For the Sixty Sixth of thoſe called the Apoſtolical Canons, <hi>Ordering that any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who deſtour'd a Virgin, ſhould either Marry her, or have no other Wife during her Life:</hi> It is nothing to his purpoſe, but rather againſt Poligamy and Concubinage.</p>
            <p>As to his Inſtances of <hi>Conſtantinus Chlorus,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Greats having Concubines, and being receiv'd by the Chriſtians into pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Authority notwithſtanding, It's Forreign to his purpoſe, the Chriſtians were Subject to former Emperours who were the worſt and lendeſt of Men, it not being i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:61505:40"/> their Power to hinder or advance them at that time, and whatever was the Practice of the Chriſtians then: If they either commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Fornication themſelves, or Countenanc'd it in others; they did thereby Act contrary to the <hi>truly Apoſtolical Canons,</hi> Act. 15. Commanding them to abſtain from Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the repeated Injunctions of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to flee Fornication, which properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, as has been already prov'd, uncleanneſs us'd by unmarried Perſons; and as for Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, or defiling the Marriage Bed, which the ſaid Princes muſt have been guilty of, by their Concubinage, it's every where Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by God and Man, tho the Chriſtians in thoſe times might perhaps neither have Power, nor think it prudent to quarrel with thoſe Emperours that were but juſt then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to ſee the Dawn of the Goſpel Light, which utterly Condemns all ſuch things. Nor can our Author make it appear, but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd them as well as one of our Biſhops did <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. and yet the Proteſtants did not think fit, neither to quarrel with his own Title to the Crown, nor thoſe of his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; tho perhaps there might have been good Reaſon to Queſtion Queen <hi>Marys</hi> Legit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy, and yet our Author knows that the Church of <hi>England</hi> neither approves of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage, Inceſt, nor Adultery; So falſe and inconcludent is his Argument. Beſides, our Author Conceals, that <hi>Conſtantius Chlorus</hi> was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61505:40"/> no declared Chriſtian, tho a Great Favourer of 'em, and that he was forc'd to abandon <hi>Helena</hi> and Marry <hi>Theodora;</hi> Step Daughter to the Emperor <hi>Maximianus Hercules,</hi> who thereupon made him <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Nor does he take any notice of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Greats be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Married very young to <hi>Minervina,</hi> when it is not certain that he made profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion, nor yet when he Married <hi>Fauſta</hi> Daughter to the Emperour <hi>Maximian,</hi> one of the Greateſt haters of the Chriſtians that ever was. Neither does he take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Plague that this wretch'd Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Fauſta</hi> was to him, for being enamoured on his Son <hi>Criſpus</hi> by <hi>Minervina</hi> and not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining her end, ſhe accus'd him of a deſign to Debauch her, for which his Father put him to Death, but underſtanding the Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the Accuſation afterwards, he put her to Death too ſo diſaſtrous were the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his Poligamy.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Valentinian,</hi> the Emperor he was paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate in anger even to Madneſs, and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly as Extravagant in his Amours, the Story is very well known, that his paſſion to ſee the Empire Inſulted by ſuch an ugly deform'd Barbarous People, as the <hi>Quadi</hi> made him fall into ſuch a fit of anger as that it kill'd him, ſo that he is no very commendable Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to be followed. Neither does Mr. <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> take any notice that God did not bleſs the Marriage of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> with <hi>Juſtina</hi> his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61505:41"/> Wifes Maid, for ſhe became a Curſed <hi>Arrian</hi> and his Grandſon <hi>Valentinian</hi> by <hi>Galla,</hi> her Daughter became a cruel Perſecutor of the Orthodox. <hi>Valentinian</hi> did alſo make a Law in Imitation of his own Practice, as Mr. <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> Writes in Defence of his, that any Man might Marry two Wives, but ſucceeding Emperors would not allow it, the Honour of being put into the Code. Nor do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Univerſities will Honour Mr. <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> Pamphlet, with a place in any of their Libraries.</p>
            <p>As to his falſe pretence of Concubinage, or Poligamies being allowed by the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, it is ſo groſs it needs no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation. Any Man that has read the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies of <hi>Tertullian, Clemens Alexandrinus, Origen</hi> againſt <hi>Celſus,</hi> or any thing of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtory will find the contrary, and for ſuch as cannot have the opportunity of peruſing thoſe Authors themſelves, I refer them to the Account of what they ſaid on that Head given by the Author of Gods Judgments againſt Whoring at the End of that Book.</p>
            <p>Our Authors laſt effort is, <hi>p.</hi> 34. Where he propoſes, <hi>a Reformed Concubinage to theſe Realms, for preventing the Ruine of Royal No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Generous Families, and as an honeſt help to deſtroy thoſe foul and crying Sins of Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Adultery, which Ruine Kingdoms as well as Families.</hi> His Arguments to back this
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61505:41"/> Propoſal are, <hi>that had it not been for Concubinage, King</hi> Solomon <hi>had utterly fail'd of that Royal Raco, whence Jeſus Chriſt Lineally deſcended. That if</hi> Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander <hi>the</hi> Scot <hi>had uſed a Concubin, an Heir of his Body might have prevented thoſe dreadful Wars betwixt</hi> Bruce <hi>and</hi> Baliol <hi>for that Crown. That if</hi> Richard <hi>the II. had been allowed an Heir by a Concubine, the War betwixt the Houſes of</hi> Lancaſter <hi>and</hi> York <hi>had been preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; which at laſt was not ended but by a Son, ſprung from a Bed of Concubinage.</hi> He concludes thus; <hi>Happy was that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage of</hi> Robert <hi>the II. of</hi> Scotland, <hi>which adviſed to by a Parliament of that Nation, gave Birth to that Family of the</hi> Stuarts, <hi>which have made both</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>and</hi> Scotland <hi>exceeding happy; and being grafted into the Family of the</hi> Welch <hi>Teudors of the Royal Blood of</hi> England, <hi>another Family ſprang from a Bed of Concubinage, are to this day reigning over both Kingdoms: Which, if ſo, let no Man by Corrupt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Cuſtoms, go about to ſtain the Legitimacy of ſuch a Race of Princes,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:61505:42"/> 
               <hi>as both</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland <hi>have Reaſon to remember with Praiſe and Thankſgiving to God; eſpecially for</hi> Charles <hi>the I. of Bleſſed and Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying Memory, the Gracious Gift of God, for whoſe bleſſed ſake Good Things may juſtly be expected in time, both unto his Royal Race, and theſe his Kingdoms. And thus much may ſerve, in Vindication of this Reſpondent for Bedding with</hi> Mary Tomkins.</p>
            <p>Our Author here, as every where elſe, hath diſcover'd himſelf to be a Phyſitian of no Value; for if they may be call'd ſo, who preſcribe a Remedy worſe than the Diſeaſe, then certainly he deſerves that Title. Suffering is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preferable to Sin; and it's bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Ten Thouſand Families ſhould be Extinguiſh'd, than that any one Man ſhould run the risk of his Soul, to keep them up. Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Paſſion for <hi>Concubinage</hi> doth ſo effectually blind him, that he can't ſee an Inch b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore his Noſe; for had he but look'd into that very Inſtance of <hi>Robert Stuart</hi>'s Concubinage, he might havd ſeen what
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61505:42"/> 
               <hi>Buchanan,</hi> the <hi>Scotch</hi> Hiſtorian, ſays concerning it, <hi>viz. Quae res poſtea tam numeroſam familiam prope Extinxit,</hi> i. e. Which Affair had well-nigh extinguiſh'd that numerous Family afterward. And becauſe our Author reckons this one of the happieſt Inſtances that can be, to advance Concubinage. I ſhall treſpaſs upon the <hi>Reader</hi>'s Patience a little, to demonſtrate the contrary.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, our Author aſſerts falſly, that this Concubinage was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by the Parliament, whereas it is plain, that if ſhe was his Concubine at all, it was when a private Man: For <hi>Buchanan</hi> ſays he married her after Queen <hi>Eupham</hi>'s Death; ſo that then ſhe was no Concubine. In the next place he falſly belies the Family of the <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arts,</hi> in ſaying that this Concubinage gave Birth to them; for both <hi>Cambden</hi> and <hi>Buchanan</hi> derive their Original from <hi>Bancho Thane</hi> of <hi>Loqhuaber,</hi> of the Blood-Royal of <hi>Scotland;</hi> who being murder'd by <hi>Mackbeth,</hi> the Tyrant, about the Year of our Lord, 1050. his Son <hi>Fleanchus</hi> fled into <hi>North-Wales,</hi> where
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61505:43"/> he married the Daughter of <hi>Griffith Lewellin,</hi> Prince of the Country, and by her had a Son, call'd <hi>Walter;</hi> who being a Valiant Man, and Favourite to King <hi>Malcolm</hi> III. that kill'd <hi>Mackbeth,</hi> he was (for defeating the <hi>Galloway.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and killing their General,) created Lord Steward of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whence the Family took Sirname; and <hi>Robert,</hi> whom we now treat of, being Son to another <hi>Walter Stuart,</hi> by King <hi>Robert Bruce</hi>'s Daughter, was the firſt of 'em, who enjoy'd the Crown: So that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> wrongs the Royal Family, both as to the Honour of their Original, which was Lawful, and not Spurious; and alſo as to their Antiquity, by 320 Years, for ſo long had they been call'd by the Name of <hi>Stuart,</hi> before they came to the Crown.</p>
            <p>But then, as to the Effects of this Concubinage, they were the moſt dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that almoſt any Hiſtory gives an Account of: For <hi>John,</hi> the Eldeſt Son, by <hi>Elizabeth Moor;</hi> who, when he came to the Crown, was call'd <hi>Robert</hi> the III. becauſe of the Hatred the <hi>Scots</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:61505:43"/> had to the Name of <hi>John,</hi> on the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>John Baliol,</hi> who betray'd their Liberty to our <hi>Edward</hi> I. and the ill Fate of King <hi>John</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and King <hi>John</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> This <hi>Robert,</hi> I ſay, had nothing of the Spirit of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo that he was tyranniz'd over by his Brother <hi>Robert,</hi> the ſecond Son of <hi>Elizabeth Moor,</hi> who ſtarved his eldeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, Prince <hi>David,</hi> to Death, in the Caſtle of <hi>Falkland,</hi> and forc'd the younger, call'd <hi>James,</hi> (afterwards <hi>James</hi> the I. of <hi>Scotland</hi>) to flee the Kingdom, and he was taken by the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> as bound to <hi>France. Alexander</hi> the youngeſt of <hi>Elizabeth Moor</hi>'s Sons, was a bloody cruel Man; and beſides other Inhumane Acts, burnt the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Cathedral of <hi>Elgin,</hi> the fineſt in all <hi>Scotland,</hi> becauſe he could not find the Biſhop of <hi>Murray,</hi> whom he deſign'd to have murder'd. And his Son <hi>Alexander</hi> was as barbarous as the Father; and Plunder'd and Murder'd his Neighbours. The Misfortune of Prince <hi>James</hi> afflicted his Father, King <hi>Robert,</hi> ſo ſenſibly, that he refuſed to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61505:44"/> be comforted, and ſtarv'd himſelf to Death. After which, his Brother, the Inhumane <hi>Robert,</hi> Reign'd under the Title of Governour; and not only kept his Nephew, <hi>James,</hi> from the Crown, during his Life, but left the Government to his own Son <hi>Murdo,</hi> who alſo kept it in his own Hands; till being diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd by the Rebellious Temper of his own Sons, he ſummoned a Parliament, and by their Advice call'd home King <hi>James</hi> I. from <hi>England;</hi> who, after his Return, made a terrible Havock among the other Princes of the Blood; cut off <hi>Murdo Stuart,</hi> Duke of <hi>Albany,</hi> and his two Sons, and baniſhed others of the Name. Upon which, <hi>James,</hi> Duke <hi>Murdo</hi>'s youngeſt Son, ſurpriz'd and kill'd the King's Uncle, and fled into <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Hiſtorian obſerves, that all this Diſorder and Diſcord in the Royal Family, was fomented by <hi>Walter,</hi> Earl of <hi>Athol,</hi> eldeſt Son to King <hi>Robert Stuart,</hi> by Queen <hi>Euphaim,</hi> his Lawful Wife, his Deſign being to have all the Poſterity of <hi>Elizabeth Moor,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubine, extinguiſh'd, that ſo the Crown
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61505:44"/> might devolve upon himſelf: which he thought might be eaſily effected, if he could but have got King <hi>James</hi> the I. taken off; which he likewiſe compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, having procured him to be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd in his Bed Chamber, as he lodg'd in the <hi>Dominicans</hi> Cloyſter near Perth, on a Journey. Upon which, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility aſſembling from all parts of the Kingdom, they purſued the Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers with ſo much Vigor, that all the Conſpirators were put to Death in 40 Days: And <hi>Walter,</hi> Earl of <hi>Athol,</hi> who was the Author of the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and <hi>Robert Graham,</hi> who actually murder'd the King, were put to death in ſuch a cruel manner, that the <hi>Reader</hi> will not think his time loſt to peruſe the Account of it, as follows. <hi>Walter</hi>'s Execution took up three Days; on the firſt he was put into a Cart, to which there was an Engine faſtned, that hoiſted him up by Ropes and Pullies, and let him down again to the Ground, which rack'd and looſened all his Joints, and put him to incredible Pain; then he was ſet on a Pillory, with a Red-hot
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61505:45"/> Iron Crown on his Head, and this Motto; The King of all Traytors, which was reckon'd the Accompliſhment of what had been foretold him by Witches, whom he had Conſulted to know whether he ſhould come to the Crown or not, <hi>viz.</hi> That he ſhould be crown'd in a great Concourſe of People. The ſecond Day he was bound upon a Hurdle, and dragg'd at a Horſes Tail through <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> On the third he was bound to a Plank, ript up alive, and had his Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els firſt, and afterwards his Heart thrown into the Fire; his Head was fixed on a Pole, and his Quarters diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted into the chief Towns of the Kingdom. <hi>Robert Graham,</hi> his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, was carried through the City in a Cart, with his Hand nail'd to a Gallows, the Executioner in the mean time run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning burning Irons into all the fleſhy Parts of his Body, and then he was quarter'd as the former, ſays <hi>Buchanan.</hi> All this was the effect of that <hi>Concubinage,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> tells us was ſo happy; ſo that inſtead of Concubinages prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ruine of Royal Families, I have
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61505:45"/> his own Inſtance upon him, to prove, that it well nigh endanger'd the Ruin of our own Royal Family, which is the moſt antient in the Weſtern World; or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for what's known in the whole U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe. And ſo far is our Author's Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion from being true, that all Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Sacred and Prophane, abound with Inſtances of Families and Nations being ruin'd by Concubinage, and other ſorts of Whoredom. For the Proof of which, I muſt again refer the Reader to that Book call'd, <hi>God's Judgments upon Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> where the Inſtances are none of 'em taken from Romances, as thoſe in the Book, call'd, <hi>God's Revenge againſt Adultery and Murder;</hi> but from appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Hiſtories; and may be of very good uſe to be read by the Youth of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd Age.</p>
            <p>His Propoſal of Concubinage, as a Remedy againſt Whoredome and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, is wholly ridiculous, and contrary to the Experience of all Eyes. The <hi>Jews</hi> were as guilty of thoſe Crimes as any People in the World, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Uſe of Concubines. Nay,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61505:46"/> 
               <hi>David</hi> himſelf, a Man according to God's own Heart, did not find this a ſufficient Remedy. The Prophets are full of Complaints againſt the <hi>Jews, for aſſembling by Troops in the Harlot's Houſes,</hi> and <hi>Neighing every one after his Neighbours Wife,</hi> Jer. Chapters 3. &amp; 5. In his 23d. he complains, that <hi>the Land is full of Adultery;</hi> and it ſeems they had ſuch Prieſts and Prophets too as Mr. <hi>Butler;</hi> for in the 14th. Verſe he ſays, <hi>I have ſeen alſo in the Prophets of Jeruſalem an horrible thing; they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery, and walk in Lies; they ſtrengthen alſo the Hands of the Evil Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that none of them doth return from his VVickedneſs:</hi> Exactly Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Practice. <hi>Solomon</hi> in the 7th. of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> gives us a Parabolical Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Nightwalkers, and ſtroling Whoremongers &amp; Whores of his time, tho there's no doubt but his Subject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves in Herds of Concubines, according to his Example; yet he tells us, <hi>That at the Window of his Houſe he look'd through his Caſement, and beheld among the ſimple ones</hi> (Cauſe enough
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61505:46"/> to make our witty Debauchees fall out with the Bible, to call them Simple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons) <hi>a young Man, void of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, paſſing through the Street, near her Corner; and he went the way to her Houſe in the twilight in the Evening, in the black and dark Night, and behold there met him a Woman, with the Attire of an Harlot, and ſubtil of Heart, ſo ſhe caught him, and kiſſed him, and with an impudent Face ſaid unto him, This day have</hi> I <hi>paid my Vows,</hi> (or I have juſt been at Church, and come from Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) <hi>therefore came I forth to meet thee diligently to ſeek thy Face, and I have found thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He goeth after her ſtraightway, as an Ox goeth to the Slaughter, or as a Fool to the Correction of the Stocks, till a Dart ſtrike through his Liver,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> might as well have propoſed the breaking down of Dikes and Banks, to prevent Inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as Concubinage to prevent Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. The practice of all Nations where it is allow'd is ſufficient to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:61505:47"/> convince him of his Miſtake. Who are more abominably Luſtful than the <hi>Turks,</hi> and yet they allow Poligamy? and indeed the Reaſon is plain, why it ſhould be ſo. There's too much Truth in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proverb, <hi>Once a Whore, and always a Whore,</hi> &amp; it will hold as well of the other Sex. Let once a Man prove unfaithful to the Wife of his Youth, whom he married in the Vigor and Strength of Affection, it will be found that it is not one or two Concubines that ſhall ſerve him. We find by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Record, that it was ſo among the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> and Hiſtory and Experience ſhews, that it hath always been ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Nations.</p>
            <p>Our Author's Propoſal is much like <hi>Lycurgus</hi>'s Laws, that he propoſed to the <hi>Spartans</hi> for a Community of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; which ſo long as they were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, ſays <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Life, the Women were far from that <hi>Scandalous Liberty,</hi> that they were afterwards ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd of, and yet one of theſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces was, <hi>That their Children ſhould not be begot by the firſt Commers</hi> (that is
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61505:47"/> their Husbands) <hi>but the beſt Men that could be found,</hi> as if there could be any thing more Scandalous: So that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi>'s Propoſal, if put in practice, would juſt ſave us from Whoredom and Adultery, as much as <hi>Lycurgus's</hi> Laws ſav'd the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> of whom <hi>Geradas</hi> ſaid, <hi>That it was as impoſſible to find an Adulterer in</hi> Sparta, <hi>as to find a Bull with a Neck ſo long, that he could ſtand on one ſide of a Mountain, and drink of a River on the other ſide,</hi> which could have no other Meaning, if <hi>Lycurgus</hi>'s Laws were obſerv'd, than that Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was ſo common among the <hi>Spartans,</hi> that it had loſt its Name; and ſo they knew not what was call'd ſo.</p>
            <p>There's no thinking Man but will eaſily be convinc'd, that the Natural Reſult of Concubinage muſt needs be Whoredom. All thoſe who obſerve the Courſe of Nature in the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Production of Mankind, allow that the number of Males and Females born, is upon the Matter equal; and the ſame may be obſerv'd in our Weekly Bills. I ſhall only inſtance the General
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61505:48"/> Bill for the Year 1697. wherein we find 8062 Males baptized, and but 7767 Females, ſo that the Majority on the ſide of the Males, is 255, to which we ſhall add 293 Women dead in Childbed, which is a Diſtemper Women are only obnoxious to, and being Natural and Conſtant, will go far towards a Ballance for the Numbers of Men ſlain now and then by War, eſpecially if we conſider that the Widows and Female Infants chiefly, of ſuch as are ſlain in Battle, have their Lives many times ſhortned for want of one to take care of 'em; and by being expos'd to hard Labour, and ſhifts for a Livelihood. So that if Concubinage ſhould be allow'd, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of Neceſſity that all Men could not be ſupplied, which would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occaſion their breaking in upon one anothers Properties, and abundance of Confuſion and Blood-ſhed.</p>
            <p>In the next place it infalliby hinders Propagation; for ſeeing the Numbers of Men and Women are upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter equal by the Courſe of Nativity, it's an Evidence that the God of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61505:48"/> deſign'd no more but one Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for one Man at a time, that there were nothing to be ſaid for it from the Scriptures. And that Concubinaries hinder Propagation; not only by En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſing two, three, or more Women to themſelves, by which they deprive other Men of having any, but alſo by being unable to perform Conjugal Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to ſo many at a time, ſo that they loſe their Teeming Seaſon, is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable thus; and we may appeal to common Experience for the Truth of it, <hi>viz.</hi> That when two Perſons are married together of equal Years, and proportionable Strength, it's found that they are ſufficient to ſatisfie one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if Sickneſs or ſome other Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent don't prevent it; and they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally moſt prolifick, and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren moſt robuſt and healthful; and therefore it were to be wiſh'd that Chriſtian Magiſtrates and Nations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd themſelves more to have good Laws made for encouraging Marriage, &amp; preventing Matches of unſuitable Years; and finding ſome Expedient to obviate
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61505:49"/> thoſe Obſtructions of Marriages, which are many times occaſion'd by waiting for Matches of equal Quality and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. If ſuch a Method were taken, abundance of Uncleanneſs might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, more People would be propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Diſhonour of Families of Quality provided againſt; which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens but too too often, ſometimes by Fornication, and ſometimes by their Daughters throwing themſelves away upon unworthy Fellows. Therefore it were Requiſite there ſhould be Laws made for beſtowing young People in Marriage aſſoon as they come to be Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riageable, and likewiſe to provide againſt the general Uncleanneſs that reigns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Seamen.</p>
            <p>But to return from this Digreſſion, ſeeing Nature and Experience teaches us, that one Woman of proportionable Years is ſufficient to ſatisfie a Man, it's impoſſible that one Man can ordinarily ſatisfie two or more Women, and by conſequence lays them under Tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to ſatisfie themſelves ſome other way, which it's evident they generally
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:61505:49"/> do, Nature it ſelf teaches Men to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor a Rival in the Marriage-Bed; and <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that Jealouſie is the Rage of a Man, why then ſhould we not think that it is the ſame with Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? Scripture and Hiſtory inform us that Co-wives, or Wives and Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, could never agree. <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Hagar, Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leah, Annah</hi> and <hi>Penninah,</hi> are Inſtances of it in Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, where the Fear of God prevail'd, and was carefully taught. Beſides, it is impoſſible that a Man can love them equally, and the Party neglected will always be uneaſie, which muſt una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably occaſion continual Jars and Diſcords, both betwixt the different Wives, and the Off-ſpring of thoſe Wives. Thus <hi>Leah</hi> complains that her Siſter had bereft her of her Husband, and was forced to purchaſe his due Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence, with her Son's Mandrakes. And thus <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren could not endure him, becauſe he was one of the Beloved Sons of the Beloved Wife. It's needleſs to inſtance in any more; we have juſt now ſeen a Contexture of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61505:50"/> Tragical Murders, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> occaſion'd by <hi>Concubinage</hi> in the Family of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> and it's not many Years, ſince a Son of Concubinage of that ſame Family, coſt this Kingdom abundance of Lives. Then certainly God nor Nature can never be the Authors or Inſtitutors of Concubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, which always was, and for ever muſt be attended, with ſuch diſmal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences.</p>
            <p>It is alſo worth our Obſervation that Hiſtories are full of Inſtances of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines, becoming enamour'don, or being defiled by the Sons of their own Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands. Thus <hi>Bilhah</hi> by <hi>Judah, David</hi>'s Concubines by <hi>Abſalom, Fauſta</hi> on <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine the Great</hi>'s Son, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which is plain, that it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for one Man to ſatisfie the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of many Women; they muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily burn, and lay hold of every Opportunity, to quench their Flame, and many times commit Crimes againſt Nature, rather than not have it effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>It deſerves likewiſe to be conſider'd, that tho it obſtructs Propagation in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61505:50"/> yet it many times increaſes parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Families to that degree, that it is impoſſible for the Father to provide for them. And therefore if he be worſe than an Infidel in the Apoſtle's Senſe, who does not provide for his own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, he muſt be doubly worſe, who takes ſuch a Courſe, as renders it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to provide for them. And I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> is ſenſible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of his Impoveriſhment, by his <hi>Poligamy,</hi> (which is the uſual Reward of Whoredom) and needs not go out of his own Family, for Inſtances of Jarring Wives, and quarrelling Children, whom he has made himſelf uncapable to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for Yet ſo Kind and Good-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd a Man he is, that he propoſes <hi>Concubinage,</hi> to prevent the Ruine of other Families, which has actually ruin'd his own. This is right Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, who tempted our firſt Parents to do that which had ruin'd himſelf; and I muſt needs tell Mr. <hi>Butler,</hi> that in this he acts more like a Preacher of <hi>Sodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> than a Preacher of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:61505:51"/>
            <p>Let us ſuppoſe that the Pious and Learned Stateſmen of theſe Realms ſhould follow his Advice, and get a Law enacted for <hi>Concubinage.</hi> We ſhould quickly ſee ſuch Pious Effects of his Pious Advice, as thoſe I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy mention'd, and many more; as Grave Matrons, who brought Eſtates to their Husbands, and have bleſſed them with a hopeful Off-ſpring, turn'd out of their Husband's Beds, and young ſprightly Girls ſupplying their place; and ſo the good old Woman and her Off-ſpring muſt be neglected, and the young Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubine and her Bantlings dandled. O! what a wonderful Pious Harmony this would make in the Ears of the Nation! And I ſuppoſe that Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> would, in this Caſe, quickly have ſuch another Peal rung in his Ears by <hi>Mary Tomkins,</hi> as now he has by <hi>Martha Perkins,</hi> and then he would think it a compleat Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynder to tell her, that he might as well hugg a young Wench, as old <hi>David</hi> hugg'd young <hi>Abiſhag.</hi> But I would have him to remember the Saying of his old Brother Lecher <hi>Ovid, Turpe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilis</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:61505:51"/> 
               <hi>Amor.</hi> I muſt beg the <hi>Reader</hi>'s Pardon, for writing ſuch Stuff, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them to conſider what an Effronted Author I have to deal with, that dares to preach up <hi>Concubinage</hi> to three Nations, almoſt drown'd already by a Deluge of Uncleanneſs, let out upon them in the late Reigns.</p>
            <p>I dare venture to ſay, that ſuch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as have given good Eſtates with their Daughters, would take it very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly to have them turn'd out of their Beds, and their Grand-children expos'd to the World, to make room for their Maids, or any other Miſſes, and their Brats. I dare alſo preſume that Pious Fathers would be very ſorry to ſee their hopeful Sons, and Heirs to their Eſtates, betake themſelves to Kennels of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines, and ſquander their Ancient Paternal Eſtates among a Spurious Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring. It's not to be doubted but Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Matrons would grieve at the Heart, to have their beloved Daughters expoſed to the Inconvenience of having but an Husband by halves, and liable to be turn'd out by the next handſome Face.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61505:52"/> There's no queſtion to be made but our Pious Stateſmen would think it the greateſt Calamity that could befall the Nation, to have its ancient Honour ſo much debaſed, as it muſt neceſſarily be by a Spurious Brood, and therefore none of 'em, I hope, will blame me for treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> thus, ſeeing all theſe are the Natural Conſequences of his Beaſtly Propoſal.</p>
            <p>And I am very well ſatisfied, that no Man, who has any Regard to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, will think that ſuch an Author ought to be treated ſoftly, who throws ſo much Dirt upon our Bleſſed Saviour's Conception and Birth, as to compare it with any thing Humane, and to ask ſuch Blaſphemous Queſtions as thoſe, <hi>P. 32. Whether God Almighty ever does any thing Ordinarily or Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily which he forbids us to do? or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Saviour's Conception and Birth were ſtain'd with Fornication or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency, becauſe perform'd out of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage?</hi> Such Queſtions from a <hi>Jew</hi> or a <hi>Turk</hi> might be expected; but out of the Mouth of a Preacher of the Goſpel
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61505:52"/> are unpardonable. Did not the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Man know that our Saviour's Body was form'd by the Power of the Holy Ghoſt, in a Super-natural Manner, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtain of Humane Corruption? Was there any thing in that which look'd like the Breach of Divine or Humane Law, as there is in the Caſe now in Queſtion. I pray God that this Blaſphemy may be forgiven him; but the thought is ſo Extravagant and Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; that it looks as if he were Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally given up of God to the Luſts of his own Heart.</p>
            <p>His Inſtance, that <hi>Solomon</hi> had fail'd of that Royal Race, whence our Bleſſed Saviour deſcended, had it not been for <hi>Concubinage,</hi> is much of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; does not our Author know, that he who was able of the Stones to raiſe up Children to <hi>Abraham,</hi> could have raiſed up a Seed to <hi>David</hi> without <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage?</hi> And that does not at all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port any thing of God's allowing of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage,</hi> more than he does of Adultery and Inceſt, which he hath expreſly forbid, as I have ſhew'd already. But,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61505:53"/> beſides, I ſhall turn his Inſtance againſt himſelf thus; That had not <hi>Solomon</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted his Strength by <hi>Concubinage,</hi> he might have left Lawful Iſſue enough be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, and therefore it was his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage</hi> that endanger'd the failure of the Royal Line; And thus <hi>Saul</hi> had four Sons by <hi>Ahinoam</hi> one Wife, when <hi>Solomon</hi> of a Thouſand Wives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines had but one Son.</p>
            <p>His Inſtance of <hi>Alexander,</hi> King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> is falſe; for he left a Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child behind him, who was Heireſs to his Crown; but ſhe dying before Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, the Competition betwixt the next Heirs happen'd, who would never have yielded to the Son of a Concubine. And the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> afterwards found out a better and more honourable Expedient than Mr <hi>Butler's, viz.</hi> that any future Controverſie about the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion ſhould be determin'd by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as may be ſeen in <hi>Buchanan's Hiſtory;</hi> and it is not very long ſince the Parliaments of both <hi>Nations</hi> had a bleſſed Opportunity of ſettling a diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Succeſſion, without Mr. <hi>Butler's</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:61505:53"/>
            <p>Then as to his Inſtance of <hi>Richard</hi> the II. any Body that has read that Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory knows, that the War began in his own time; not becauſe he wanted Iſſue, but becauſe he unjuſtly ſeiz'd the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter</hi>'s Eſtate, and deſign'd to baniſh his Son for ever; who landed in <hi>England</hi> when <hi>Richard</hi> was in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and left the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> his Uncle, to govern in his Abſence.</p>
            <p>But the Nation was ſo much diſpleas'd with <hi>Richard,</hi> that the Duke of <hi>York</hi> was not able to reſiſt the Duke of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> ſo that the Nation in Parliament charg'd <hi>Richard</hi> with the Breach of his Coronation Oath in 32 Articles, oblig'd him to reſign the Crown to the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> who came to the Poſſeſſion of the Throne that way, before <hi>Richard</hi> was murder'd. So that it was not his want of Iſſue which began that War, nor the want of Lineal Heirs, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of <hi>Lionel,</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Right precedent to that of the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> But the Parliament laid their Claim aſide, as in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity they would have done that of his
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61505:54"/> Son's, if he had left any, conſidering the prevailing Intereſt and Victorious Arms of the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter;</hi> but Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> is much ſuch another Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian as he is a Divine. And now let him ſee to it whether he hath ſufficiently vindicated his Bedding with <hi>Mary Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> or Concubinage in general, by thoſe or any other Inſtances.</p>
            <p>But becauſe Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> ſhall have all the fair Dealing imaginable, I ſhall take Notice of a Text, quoted by thoſe of his Opinion, to prove their Point, which it's like he has forgot, <hi>viz.</hi> Deut. 21. 15. <hi>If a Man have two Wives, one beloved, and another hated, and they have born him Children, both the beloved, and the hated, and if the firſt-born Son be hers that was hated; He may not make the Son of the beloved firſt-born, before the Son of the hated, which is indeed firſt born.</hi> This I quote now, leſt it ſhould be applied by him or others afterwards againſt what I have already ſaid; and the Anſwer is as follows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes</hi> here acts the part of a Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Law-giver, but not of a Spiritual
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61505:54"/> Doctor; And <hi>Poligamy</hi> being conniv'd at in the <hi>Jews</hi> at that time, He lays down Rules, to prevent Injuſtice to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the leaſt-beloved Wife.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's plain from hence, that <hi>Poliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> diſtracts the Affections of the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and naturally occaſions Injuſtice to ſome of his Offſpring, which muſt needs cauſe Hatred, Contention, and all manner of Confuſion in a Family, elſe <hi>Moſes</hi> would not have here provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Words, <hi>the Son of her that was hated,</hi> would ſeem to imply, that both the Wives were not alive to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and then it makes nothing for <hi>Poligamy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This cannot be ſuppoſed to be any thing at moſt but a meer Permiſſion of the thing, becauſe it is contrary to the Law againſt taking two Wives, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. 18. which the <hi>Karaei</hi> or <hi>Jews</hi> that adhere to the Scriptures, underſtand to be clearly prohibited by that Text.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Our Saviour and his Apoſtles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. and 15 and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 16. and 7. 2. which I have taken Notice of already,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61505:55"/> ſay, that <hi>Poligamy</hi> was forbidden; and ſeeing they ſay, Let every Man have his own Wife, and every Woman her own Husband, all that Liberty which was granted to, or aſſumed by the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> is taken away.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſt underſtands that Text, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. 18. to be againſt <hi>Poligamy,</hi> and ſays that was the Reaſon why <hi>Ruth</hi>'s Kinſman, <hi>Ruth.</hi> 4. 6. refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to marry <hi>Ruth,</hi> becauſe he had a Wife before; and that to marry ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would break the Peace of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, divide his Eſtate, and occaſion Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords amongſt the Children of the two Wives.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is not like, that God would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low two Wives to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by a Law, which ſome of the better <hi>Heathens</hi> diſapprov'd, as may be ſeen in <hi>Phocylides</hi> and <hi>Euripides;</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian</hi> made a Law againſt it, as may be ſeen, <hi>Cod. Lib. 5. Tit. 5. Leg.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Poligamy</hi> or <hi>Concubinage</hi> is againſt the Apoſtle's Prohibition of Married Perſons defrauding one another, it being impoſſible for one Man ordinarily to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61505:55"/> more than one Woman; ſo that to marry more than one, expoſes them to the Danger of <hi>Satan</hi>'s Tentation for their Incontinence; of which, <hi>Bilhah</hi> and <hi>David</hi>'s Concubines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſad Inſtances.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Apoſtle could not ſay, Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Woman have her own or proper Husband <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> if he allowed. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinage,</hi> for then he ſhould be common to two or more.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That which is made one Fleſh with the Body, cannot be made a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of another Body; therefore a Man who is one Fleſh with his Wife, cannot be one Fleſh alſo with another in a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Senſe; for there can be no Union where there is a Diviſion, as in this Caſe there muſt be.</p>
            <p n="11">11. If <hi>Concubinage</hi> were allow'd, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage could be no proper Reſemblance of the Union betwixt Chriſt &amp; his Church; for Chriſt has but one Church, whereas in that Caſe a Man ſhould have more than one Wife.</p>
            <p>Some again object, that <hi>ſeeing the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle preſcribes, that he who was to be</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:61505:56"/> 
               <hi>choſen Biſhop, ſhould be the Husband of one Wife,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 2. <hi>Poligamy was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in others.</hi> To which 'tis anſwer'd that many of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> in thoſe times had two Wives. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it's ſuppoſed they were tolerated to keep them during Life, or at leaſt till they were confirm'd in the Faith; but it would have been ſcandalous to have had ſuch for Miniſters or Biſhops.</p>
            <p n="2">2, The Law of <hi>Monogamy</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd by Chriſt, and Preach'd up by this ſame Apoſtle elſewhere, he cannot be imagin'd to allow it here.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Reaſon of this Injunction is ſuppos'd to be, that it would have been accounted ſcandalous in Chriſtian Biſhops, to come ſhort of the Heathen Prieſts in Continency, who were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to have two Wives, as may be ſeen in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and other Authors.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It cannot be thought that any ſuch thing was allow'd in the ancient Church, when to marry twice was by them ſo much ſcrupled, that ſome think the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle forbids ſuch Perſons here to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſen Biſhops.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:61505:56"/>5. <hi>Beza</hi> on the Place tells us, that not only. Bigamy and Poligamy were forbid by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Canons, but likewiſe the Marriage of ſuch Perſons as had raſhly divorc'd their Wives. And Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> on the Place quotes <hi>Theophilact</hi> and <hi>Athenagoras</hi> for it; That Marriage after Divorce was forbidden to the Antient Chriſtians. So falſly has Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> alledged the Cuſtoms of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> to defend his Practice.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with what <hi>Willet</hi> ſays on 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. that if it ſeems ſtrange that the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs</hi> ſhould ſo long continue in an Error unreform'd; The like Inſtance is given, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8. 17. where the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are ſaid not to have kept the Feaſt of Tabernacles, from <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s time till then, by the ſpace almoſt of 1000 Years. But tho God winked at thoſe times of Ignorance, he now calleth all Men to repent; and the worſt I wiſh Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> is, that he would glorifie God, by confeſſing his Sin, and taking Shame upon himſelf, and not add Fuel to thoſe Flames of Uncleanneſs, which have well-nigh ruin'd the Nation already, and will bring down the Flames of Divine Vengeance upon us, if we don't Repent and Reform.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:61505:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
            <p n="1">1. GOD's Judgments againſt Whoring. Being an Eſſay to a General Hiſtory of it, from the Creation of the World to the Reign of <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> (which, according to common Computation, is 5190 Years) and from thence down to the preſent Year 1697. Being a Collection of the moſt Remarkable Inſtances of Uncleanneſs, that are to be found in Sacred or Prophane Hiſtory, during that time; with Obſervations thereon. Pr. <hi>3s. 6d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Secrer Hiſtory of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> from the Reſtoration of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. down to the Abdication of the late King <hi>James</hi> Writ at the Requeſt of a Noble Lord, and Convey'd to him in Letters, by—late Secretary, Interpreter to the Marquis of <hi>Louvois;</hi> who, by that Means, had the Peruſal of all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Minutes between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> for many Years. The whole conſiſting of Secret Memoirs, which have hitherto lain conceal'd, as not being diſcoverable by any other Hand. Publiſhed from the Original Papers, by <hi>D. Jones,</hi> Gent. Price <hi>5s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. By the ſame Author, A Continuation of the Secret Hiſtory of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> from the Abdication of the late King <hi>James,</hi> in 1688. to the year 1696. Together with the Tragical Hiſtory of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> from the firſt Riſe of that Family, in the Year 1068. down to the Death of her Late Majeſty, Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> of Bleſſed Memory. Price <hi>5s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Sold by <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
